<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eleutheria, or, An idea of the Reformation in England and a history of non-conformity in and since that Reformation : with predictions of a more glorious reformation and revolution at hand ... / mostly compiled and maintain'd from unexceptionable writings of conformable divines in the Church of England ; to which is added, The conformists reasons for joining with the nonconformists in divine worship, by another hand.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50123</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12776478</idno>
  <idno type="VID">93774</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264193887</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1888</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12776478</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50123)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 361:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eleutheria, or, An idea of the Reformation in England and a history of non-conformity in and since that Reformation : with predictions of a more glorious reformation and revolution at hand ... / mostly compiled and maintain'd from unexceptionable writings of conformable divines in the Church of England ; to which is added, The conformists reasons for joining with the nonconformists in divine worship, by another hand.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>iv, 135 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.R. and sold by Sam. Philips ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cotton Mather. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Michigan Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Reformation --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93774:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93774:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ELEƲTHERIA:</hi> OR, An <hi>Idea</hi> of the REFORMATION IN ENGLAND: AND A <hi>History</hi> of NON-CONFORMITY in and since that <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With PREDICTIONS of a more glorious REFORMATION and REVOLUTION at hand. Written in the year 1696.</p>
            <p>Mostly compiled and maintain'd from unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionable Writings of Conformable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, The <hi>Conformists</hi> Reasons for joining with the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> in Divine Worship.</p>
            <p>By another Hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. R.</hi> and sold by <hi>Sam. Philips</hi> Bookseller at <hi>Boston</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93774:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:93774:2"/>
            <head>THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THIS Treatise I received by a Trader from <hi>New-England</hi> from an unknown hand (a Learned <hi>Nonconformist</hi> there, as I guess him to be.) I had not time to have the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of some judicious Divine here (for a number of them was desired to be sent this Season into those parts) therefore I have adventured to print it on my own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and tho I will not presume to be a competent judg, yet I may say this, that it is a brief, smart, and (I hope) a true History of the darkness of Popery, the first Rise of the Reformation, and the great struggles for further Reformation ever since; and all this made good by
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:93774:3"/> the Writings of many Divines of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Printer having left room at the latter end, I thought good to add a Sheet which I received from a Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I hope will not offend the Author of this Treatise, in as much as it may be use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Reader to convince him that there are some conformable Divines, even at this time, that heartily desire and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor after Union and Communion with all the faithful in the Land, whether <hi>Conformists</hi> or <hi>Nonconformists;</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> having in her Articles given this definition of a Church, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The visible Church of Christ is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of faithful Men, in which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments be duly administred according to Christ's Ordinance, in all those things that of necessity are requisite to the same.</hi> I leave the Reader to make the Inference.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 18. 1698.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Vade, Liber, quanquam sis parvus mole, sed amplum Lectori Fructum det Deus Omnipotens.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:93774:3"/>
            <head>TO THE BOOKSELLER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS is not the first time, that you have been address'd from an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Hand,</hi> with matters which were worthy to be made known, and which by your charitable care have been made known to the whole <hi>English Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character which you deservedly have, even in <hi>America,</hi> as well as <hi>Europe,</hi> is that of <hi>a good Man;</hi> and agreeably to that Character, you will by the Publication of the <hi>Manuscript</hi> here sent you, come to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>with good Tidings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Author</hi> of this <hi>Manuscript</hi> lies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed from you, and from all its Readers, only that he may, till a fitter Opportunity, preserve his <hi>Teeth</hi> from some few <hi>kicking Unreasonables:</hi> But the <hi>Matter</hi> of it is a Discourse, wherein with <hi>Truth closely followed,</hi> there is expressed such a Spirit of <hi>union</hi> with all <hi>good Men,</hi> whether <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:93774:4"/> or <hi>Dissenters,</hi> that none of <hi>them</hi> can be offended at.</p>
            <p>It cannot but be a Satisfaction unto the lovers of <hi>Truth,</hi> to be entertained with an <hi>History,</hi> thus unexceptionable: and a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of such a disposition as <hi>yours,</hi> to serve your Country and the Church of God in all its Interests, cannot but rejoice in an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to communicate unto the Publick a <hi>little Book,</hi> accommodated so much as <hi>this,</hi> unto those Interests.</p>
            <p>You will find the Composure <hi>brief;</hi> but you will find a <hi>variety</hi> of acceptable things, crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into this <hi>grateful brevity:</hi> the <hi>Stile</hi> also I hope you will find not unacceptable: and tho 'twas written in the year <hi>1696,</hi> I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose 'tis grown but the more seasonable, by being till <hi>now</hi> reserved.</p>
            <p>But all this I leave to your better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and subscribe,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your hearty (tho unknown) Friend and Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Boston</hi> in NEW-ENGLAND, <date>
                     <hi>May 10. 1698.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93774:4"/>
            <head>ELEƲTHERIA.</head>
            <p n="1">§. 1. WE have seen a <hi>great</hi> RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOLUTION, and we are e're long to see a <hi>greater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are very considerable <hi>Questions,</hi> which do, and will, and cannot <hi>but</hi> exercise the minds of good Men in the English Nation. To assist agreeable <hi>Answers</hi> unto those considerable <hi>Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> there can scarce any more significant thing be offered, than an incontestible <hi>Idea</hi> and <hi>History</hi> of the REFORMATION. And one is here brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhibited, which the consenting Pens of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Writers</hi> in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> all along here quoted, have rendred incontestible.</p>
            <p>You have here a relation and a description of a <hi>marvellous Matter,</hi> whereof I may say, as <hi>Austin</hi> once did of another Matter, <hi>Quisquis non videt, caecus: Quisquis videt, nec laudat, ingratus: Quis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis laudanti reluctatur, insanus:</hi> Those Men are <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>mad</hi> who do not acknowledg it. But the Reader is thereupon surprised with a further Advice of this importance: <hi>Believest thou? Thou shalt see yet greater things than these.</hi> And when his courteous patience hath carried him to the end of this little Treatise, he will see upon what Authority this Expectation is with so much freedom uttered; he will see that it is no <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93774:5"/>§. 2. And now, <hi>Reader,</hi> be willing to travel so far into <hi>Antiquity,</hi> as to take a view of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whereinto the <hi>Christian Church</hi> was fallen by the <hi>Apostacy,</hi> which, as the Spirit of the Lord Jesus Christ long before <hi>expresly</hi> foretold, was to come upon it. When the <hi>Imperial</hi> and <hi>Heathenish</hi> Power once flourishing at <hi>Rome,</hi> which hindred the <hi>Revelation</hi> of that <hi>wicked one,</hi> was <hi>taken out of the way;</hi> and in the <hi>fourth</hi> and <hi>fifth</hi> Century, the fierce Nations of the <hi>Northern Barbarians</hi> made their violent Assaults upon the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and carried all before 'em, with an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resistible Inundation of <hi>Desolation; Then</hi> a <hi>little Priest</hi> had opportunity to establish himself with a <hi>mixt Religion</hi> among those <hi>barbarous Nations,</hi> and then there appeared openly in the <hi>Temple of God</hi> that ANTICHRIST, who calls himself (what indeed the very name ANTICHRIST most <hi>properly</hi> signifies) The <hi>Vicar of CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Antichrist,</hi> or the <hi>Satanical Spirit,</hi> working in the <hi>Bishop of</hi> Rome, was <hi>conceived</hi> as early as <hi>twenty five</hi> years after the Ascension of our Lord, in affectations of <hi>Ecclesiastical Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency,</hi> when the Apostles accordingly gave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him; and he was compleated about <hi>six hundred</hi> and <hi>sixty six</hi> years after this, when <hi>Image-Worship</hi> was effectually pressed by the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> of the Western <hi>Babylon,</hi> with the ruin of the <hi>Iconoclastick</hi> Emperors that refused it. But between those Terms, even about the year 450, there were no less than <hi>ten</hi> Soveraign Kingdoms, which, taking advantage from the Confusions whereinto the Empire was fallen,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93774:5"/> set up for themselves; and according to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oracles, when those ten <hi>Kingdoms received their Power, then,</hi> even in that ONE HOUR, there got into the Throne the <hi>Antichristian Beast,</hi> unto whom it may be the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> had some respect in the most antient Writings of the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> which mention the <hi>Leviathan.</hi> From the <hi>Shipwreck</hi> of the <hi>Empire</hi> there were quickly gathered <hi>Planks</hi> to patch up that <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick,</hi> which they since call St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Bark:</hi> a crafty <hi>Clergy</hi> under one <hi>spiritual Monarch,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the <hi>Conquerors</hi> of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> from whom they had been <hi>conquered;</hi> obtruding upon them a <hi>Christianity</hi> disguised with <hi>Paganism,</hi> and a <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Daemons,</hi> with a mighty Lerry of <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> and Austerities of <hi>forbidding to marry, and commanding to abstain from Meats,</hi> to render the <hi>Cup of their Abomination</hi> the more inebriating. Thus the <hi>deadly Wound</hi> giv'n to the <hi>Fourth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> was healed; the <hi>Dragon</hi> that inspired it under its <hi>Heathen</hi> form, did now no less inspire it under its <hi>Christian;</hi> and the faithful People of God were not mistaken in those days, in their Conjectures upon the <hi>Signs of times,</hi> when <hi>Rome</hi>'s falling into the <hi>Gothic</hi> hands, caused them to expect and exclaim with <hi>Jerom. He that hindred is now taken out of the way; ANTICHRIST is at hand! Gregory</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> had no sooner proclaimed it, in these memorable words of his twenty eighth Epistle, <hi>Because</hi> ANTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHRIST, <hi>that Enemy of the Almighty,</hi> IS NOW AT HAND — <hi>I speak it boldly; whoever calls himself, or desires to be call'd by others, The</hi> UNIVERSAL BISHOP, <hi>is the</hi> FORE-RUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NER
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93774:6"/> OF ANTICHRIST. But <hi>Boniface</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> coming a few Months after him, obtained from the Traitor <hi>Phocas (Obtinuit mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ tamen contentione,</hi> saith <hi>Platina</hi>) The Title of THE SOVERAIGN AND UNIVERSAL BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHOP. To the Reign of the ANTICHRIST, and so of <hi>Idolatry, Persecution,</hi> and all <hi>mysteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iniquity,</hi> thus come into play, the great Lord of all <hi>Time</hi> hath allow'd a space, wearing the Denomination of TIME, TIMES, and HALF A TIME; or in plainer Expressions, <hi>twelve hundred and sixty Years;</hi> and so long all the effects of an horrible <hi>Apostacy</hi> make a very <hi>Gehinnom</hi> of that which was called <hi>CHRISTEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">§. 3. While the doleful <hi>time</hi> of three hundred and sixty Years, and the yet more doleful <hi>two times</hi> of seven hundred and twenty years were slowly <hi>wheeling</hi> about, no <hi>Tongue</hi> is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press, or <hi>Heart</hi> conceive, the lamentable Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances whereto the Holy God abandoned the World, for its indisposition to the blessed <hi>Kingdom</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ: tho Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings were then commonly dated <hi>Regnante Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sto,</hi> yet it may be truly said, that <hi>Satan</hi> then <hi>reigned,</hi> so as never more uncontrolably. It was then the <hi>Hour and Power of Darkness;</hi> the Devil (in his <hi>Vicar</hi> and <hi>Vice-Roy</hi>) was by <hi>the Wrath of God</hi> the <hi>King of</hi> Europe, and the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyer of the Faith;</hi> and it was but with too much of <hi>significancy,</hi> tho a <hi>Prosopopeia</hi> bold enough, there were then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>amed <hi>Letters of Thanks</hi> from <hi>Lucifer the Prince of Darkness, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93774:6"/> Emperor of the High Mysteries of</hi> Acheron, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>dear Allies, the Clergy of the Church of this latter Age, which his Adversary Jesus Christ calls the Congregation of the Wicked,</hi> for the <hi>help</hi> which they had given him <hi>to bring the whole World under his Dominion;</hi> and saying this, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things too justly said, <hi>Thou hast cleaved unto us, O our blessed</hi> Babylon; <hi>the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty of our Empire is by you propt up, and our intolerable loss restored!</hi> None but men intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto the degree of <hi>Campanella</hi>'s Phrensy, can dream (tho <hi>he</hi> did, and wrote it) that this <hi>Reign of the Pope</hi> was the promised <hi>Reign of our Lord:</hi> It is this <hi>papal</hi> Confusion upon the World which is by the All-wise Permission of Heaven, that which lies in the way of <hi>what according to the Promise of God we look for:</hi> And so it <hi>must,</hi> and so it <hi>will,</hi> until the <hi>wicked One be destroyed by the brightness</hi> of the second coming of him, whom we expect <hi>from Heaven as our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In those dismal days, [<hi>Reader,</hi> wilt thou not give thanks to God that thou wast not born in <hi>those</hi> days?] Clouds of thick Barbarity envelop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and overwhelmed all <hi>Schools of Literature.</hi> The famous Maxim of old <hi>John Dullard</hi> past for no less than a Maxim, <hi>Quanto eris melior Grammaticus, tanto pejor Theologus. Espencaeus,</hi> one of themselves, acknowledges that among their best Authors, <hi>Graece nosse suspectum fuerit, Hebraice proprie Haereticum. Zuinglius</hi> and <hi>Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> had like to have lost their lives for medling with those dangerous Languages, <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew.</hi> To give the Etymology of the word <hi>Alleluja,</hi> rack'd the most extended Wits of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93774:7"/> whole <hi>Ʋniversities.</hi> The best <hi>Latin</hi> they wrote was little better than the stuff in the <hi>Epistolae obscurorum virorum;</hi> the reading whereof cast the witty <hi>Erasmus</hi> into such a fit of laughter as broke an <hi>Abscess</hi> in his face, whereinto the Chirurgeons were going to make an <hi>Incision.</hi> What jejune and wretched <hi>Fooleries</hi> were the highest Learning of <hi>Colleges,</hi> the more learned <hi>Bullinger</hi> alone is a sufficient Relator: A little of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> confounded rather than expounded by the Commentaries of the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> with an heap of pitiful Cobweb-Notions, was the <hi>Flinty Diet</hi> then gnaw'd upon; and <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> roundly <hi>swears</hi> for them, that when they some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brag'd of such abilities in <hi>Disputation</hi> as would have been too hard for <hi>Aristotle</hi> himself, <hi>Ego id pro vobis dejerabo, nam quas artes vos modo exomniastis, quas nugas, &amp; quidem ex illius, ut pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, Dogmatibus, ipse si revivisceret, non intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerit, ac ne suos quidem Libros, ut vos explicatis.</hi> Their <hi>Divinity</hi> was by a Renowned Writer, who lived three hundred years ago, too truly compared unto the <hi>Apples</hi> of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that under a <hi>fair</hi> skin had nothing but <hi>Ashes</hi> and <hi>Poison. Doctors of Divinity</hi> were created, and pronounced <hi>most sufficient,</hi> who never had read the <hi>Bible,</hi> (nor indeed had they any other Bible, than that <hi>vulgar Latin,</hi> wherein one of themselves, <hi>Isi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Clarius,</hi> declares that he found <hi>fourscore thousand Errors:</hi>) and, as <hi>Erasmus</hi> reports of them, at fourscore years of Age they had stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died nothing but a few silly <hi>Sophisms;</hi> and if any thing were quoted out of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> it asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished them. <hi>Stephens</hi> and <hi>Gerhard</hi> are compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93774:7"/> Witnesses, that the Preachers of no less than half an hundred years standing, had never seen the <hi>New Testament: Musculus</hi> affirms, that multitudes of them never saw the <hi>Scriptures</hi> in their Lives; or if they ever did, it was like the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> of whom <hi>Amama</hi> tells us, that opening the <hi>Bible,</hi> he said, <hi>In truth I don't know what Book this is, but I perceive ev'ry thing in it is against us.</hi> Their <hi>Sermons</hi> were accordingly but ridiculous <hi>Harangues</hi> upon the <hi>Reliques</hi> or <hi>Merits</hi> of the <hi>Saints;</hi> or else the more exquisite <hi>Postillers</hi> made <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> or <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas,</hi> or <hi>Duns Scotus,</hi> the Oracles upon which they discoursed: <hi>Plures extiterunt</hi> (says <hi>Thanner) Thomistae quam Biblici.</hi> And as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> affirms, <hi>Aristotles Ethicks</hi> was in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Churches usually treated on; but all were generally of <hi>Hosius</hi>'s Perswasion, <hi>Longè meliori talo res Ecclesiae staturas fuisse, si nullum Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium scriptum fuisset.</hi> In those days the <hi>Face of the Earth</hi> was almost covered with <hi>Religious Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> as they called them; from whence continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally issued out the swarms of those <hi>Locusts,</hi> the several <hi>Orders</hi> of the <hi>Religious,</hi> who in the great <hi>smoke of the bottomless Pit,</hi> which they brought with them, tormented Mankind exceedingly. <hi>Alsted</hi> above one hundred years ago, reckons <hi>two hundred twenty five thousand, forty and four</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries in <hi>Christendom;</hi> in which, if we reckon only twenty persons belonging at the same time to each of these <hi>Monasteries</hi> one with another, the <hi>Sum total</hi> amounts to <hi>four Millions five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand eighty and eight Souls.</hi> If after so many Nations had utterly suppress'd these <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93774:8"/> of the Devil,</hi> they were yet so nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, what horrid Shoals of Poisoners was the World before such a suppression plagued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al? Their <hi>Cells</hi> were not the seats of the <hi>Muses</hi> and the <hi>Graces,</hi> as <hi>Mutius</hi> tells us that <hi>Charles the Great</hi> intended them, when he founded so many of them; no, they were, as <hi>Hospinian</hi> tells us, rather <hi>squalid Prisons,</hi> and such Nurse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ignorance, that, <hi>More ignorant than a Monk,</hi> was a Proverb for the <hi>most ignorant;</hi> and it was no abuse to stile the Wretches who dwelt in them, <hi>Stoicas simias, cucullata Monstra, inscitiae &amp; Cacologiae Doctores:</hi> yea they were the very <hi>Habitations of Devils, the Holds of every foul Spirit, the Cages of every hateful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Bird;</hi> and such <hi>Antichambers</hi> of Hell it self, that if after <hi>Bernard</hi>'s Invectives against them, we peruse the incontestible Accounts of them who then went under the name of the <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> reported by <hi>Petrus Cluniacensis,</hi> by <hi>Cerbo Augustinianus,</hi> by <hi>Gualo,</hi> and <hi>Nigellus,</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Polydore Virgil,</hi> and others, but especially by old <hi>Nicolaus de Clemangis,</hi> we shall wonder at the Divine Patience that the Fate of <hi>Sodom</hi> (still impending over the abominable City of <hi>Rome</hi>) did not overtake them. The <hi>King over those Children of Pride,</hi> whose Title was <hi>His Holiness,</hi> ordinarily was a very <hi>Devil</hi> for wickedness, an <hi>Heretick,</hi> a <hi>Conjurer,</hi> a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer,</hi> a <hi>Murderer,</hi> a <hi>Sodomite;</hi> such a filthy pack there was of them, that heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> with all her <hi>Nero</hi>'s, or <hi>Domitian</hi>'s, or <hi>Commodus</hi>'s, or <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liogabalus</hi>'s, could never match them: And it may be guessed, what Saints the Common
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93774:8"/> Soldiers were, when they had such Hell-brands to be their Leaders. In those days the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of our Lord Jesus Christ was ev'ry where lost in a depraved mixture of Jewish and Pagan Rites (not without additions from the <hi>Alcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran:</hi>) cursed Charms, and thousands of magical Tricks, were every where introduced, instead of our <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Institutions;</hi> insomuch that the Author of the <hi>Fasciculus Temporum</hi> says, A Monster of a Dog's Head on a Man's Body, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited unto <hi>Lewis, benè potuit monstrosum statum significare hujus Temporis:</hi> Exorcisms and Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and very diabolical Fopperies were of universal use. The Faithful were <hi>sacrilegiously</hi> cheated of the <hi>Cup</hi> in the <hi>Eucharist</hi> (tho our Lord foreseeing this, expresly bad them <hi>ALL drink of it;</hi>) and the monstrous Figment of <hi>Transubstantiation</hi> was thrust down their throats with <hi>burning Firebrands.</hi> The variegated <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> of <hi>Artolatry,</hi> and <hi>Mariolatry,</hi> and <hi>Hagiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> and <hi>Angelolatry,</hi> and <hi>Leipsanolatry,</hi> and <hi>Iko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolatry,</hi> fill'd the Devotions of Mankind. A vile Man sitting in his <hi>Pontifical Chair,</hi> was with infinite Blasphemy adored as the <hi>Lord God,</hi> and that Stile of <hi>Dominus Deus noster Papa</hi> most blasphemously usurped. And such Devilism ruled in all places, that the Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of these Periods cannot forbear crying out with <hi>Vitoduranus, O quam lamentabilis, &amp; exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crabilis deformitas Ecclesiae, illis in temporibus facta est!</hi> In those days a pretended Successor to <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> advanced by the Arts of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (and inferior Ecclesiasticks usually fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Example) exercis'd a prodigious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93774:9"/> Tyranny over the Children of Men in all their Interests: The People could not approach the <hi>Word of Life;</hi> the <hi>Bread of Life</hi> was detain'd in inaccessible Concealments, and the blind led the blind; the <hi>Colliers Creed</hi> no man might presume to go beyond: <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>absolute Obedience to the Holy See</hi> fetter'd the Consciences of Men: Laws above and beyond, and contrary to those of our Lord were imposed upon Men, so many as make huge Volumes of <hi>Canons</hi> in Folio; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, Decretals</hi> and <hi>Extravagants</hi> made a huge body of Laws for all men to observe, which wise men would even disdain to study, but say with the Prophet, <hi>Non possumus, Domine, vesci stercore humano:</hi> Laws whereof <hi>Agrippa,</hi> who was a <hi>Doctor</hi> thereof, says, <hi>Non sunt à Deo nec ad Deum, sed a corrupto hominum ingenio profecta, &amp; ad avaritiam excogitata.</hi> Filthy Lucre was all that was pursued by the greedy Dogs, who had now taken the charge of the Flocks; and the forlorn Flocks, that saw (as <hi>Mantuan</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plores it) there were
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Venalia Romae</l>
                  <l>Templa, Sacerdotes, Altaria sacra, Coronae,</l>
                  <l>Ignis, Thura, Preces, Coelum venale, Deus{que}</l>
               </q> were under all possible Temptations to fall into downright Atheism. The Marriage of Priests was made a Crime unpardonable by those that were the most profligate of Whoremasters, <hi>Qui conjugia damnando prefitentur se nasci non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buisse:</hi> And one grand <hi>Brothel-House</hi> was made of that which was called the <hi>House of God.</hi> That Sham, the Fire of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> was an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93774:9"/> that made a lewd and a vast Crew of kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish Churchmen, under a vow of Poverty, live merrily upon Rostmeat all their days. An Historian of their own asserts it with some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment concerning the one Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in particular, <hi>That there was not remaining so much Treasure in the Kingdom as these Wretches had in one three years extorted, and exported out of it, the Vessels of the Church only excepted:</hi> Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Indulgences,</hi> denominated very properly <hi>The Treasury of the Church,</hi> were, as <hi>Rivet</hi> calls them, <hi>Emulgences,</hi> whereby besotted Sinners were <hi>milk'd</hi> of all the money they had: These did, as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> expresses it, <hi>Romanorum locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los impraegnare,</hi> cram the Coffers of the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists:</hi> But so ingenuous is the <hi>Taxa Camerae Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicae,</hi> as to confess, <hi>Nota diligenter, quod hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jusmodi gratiae non conceduntur pauperibus; quià non habent, ergò non possunt consolari.</hi> A proud <hi>Prelate</hi> would set his <hi>foot</hi> upon the neck of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Emperors</hi> must hold the stirrup for mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Beggars: Crowned Heads</hi> were treated with wonderful Indignities by a <hi>Tyrant of Souls;</hi> and if any one began to dispute his Tyranny, they dreadfully thunderstruck him, embaras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him, and ruin'd him with their <hi>Anathemas;</hi> two Emperors alone were under a necessity to fight at least threescore bloody Battles against Enemies, which the <hi>Pope</hi> had raised against them. The Immunity from the secular Power claim'd by <hi>Ecclesiasticks,</hi> and the command which by means of Auricular Confession they got over the Souls of Men, put the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an intolerable Slavery to the <hi>Powers of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93774:10"/> darkness.</hi> —But hold <hi>my Pen!</hi> 'Tis here no place for thee to transcribe the Letters of <hi>Petrarch</hi> to his friends about <hi>Rome</hi>'s being the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> or the Complaints which <hi>Clemangis</hi> made several hundreds of years ago, <hi>De corrupto Ecclesiae statu,</hi> or to abridg the whole Cartloads of Books, which a whole Army of <hi>Protestants</hi> (besides Monsieur <hi>Claude</hi>) have since written in <hi>defence of the Reformation.</hi> It is enough to bring in <hi>Baronius</hi> himself, lamenting the <hi>Tempora Ecclesiae infelicissima, &amp; luctuosissima,</hi> The lamentable times, when into the Chair of <hi>Peter</hi> [Sir, Your <hi>Eminence</hi> might have call'd it, <hi>The Chair of Pestilence!</hi>] there got horribly dissolute, villanous, and infamous Monsters; when Strumpets ruled the Roast, and all holy Canons and Customs were extinguished; when our Lord Jesus Christ slept in the Ship with a profound sleep, and the violent Winds overwhelmed it, and he raised up no man to correct these things; yea, which was worst of all, there were no Disciples to awaken our Lord with their cries, but a dead sleep was upon them all.</p>
            <p n="4">§. 4. Were there no Attempts of good Men in this doleful <hi>Time,</hi> and in these woful <hi>Times,</hi> to recover the Church out of this deplorable <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacy?</hi> Yes, but unsuccessful enough, because the <hi>last Half-time</hi> of the Antichrist was not yet arrived. Many particular Witnesses of the Truth, illuminated by the Grace of Heaven, saw through the thick mists of <hi>Error</hi> in these Ages of <hi>darkness;</hi> and in the very darkest places of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93774:10"/> the Earth, which was then filled with <hi>Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Cruelty,</hi> so many were these <hi>Witnesses,</hi> that the World knows, the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of them hath made a <hi>Folio:</hi> And as those eminent men whose <hi>Heart-strings were made of a little finer Clay</hi> than the grosser part of Mankind, could not without much <hi>Abomination,</hi> behold the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Principles and Practices then commonly prevailing; so there were not a few of them, who particularly discerned the evident Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of ANTICHRIST. It is five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ago, that Abbot <hi>Joachim</hi> told the two Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> That <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist was he who was then set on high on the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolick Seat in the City of</hi> Rome; <hi>and that in the time of this Antichrist many Christians shall preserve the true Faith in Dens and Caves of the Earth, and in desart places, even until the consummation of Antichrist;</hi> and as long ago it is, that <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Blois</hi> exhorted his Friends in time to depart from the midst of that <hi>Babylon.</hi> It is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without admiration to read the most exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site Oration made by the Bishop of <hi>Saltsburgh</hi> to the <hi>States of the Empire,</hi> in the year 1240, in which he calls the <hi>Popes</hi> the <hi>Priests</hi> of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> and finds at <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Antichrist</hi> which had the <hi>ten Horns,</hi> or Kings of <hi>Europe</hi> under him. Yea, as early as the year 991, a whole Council of <hi>Gallick Bishops</hi> cried out upon the Pope, <hi>He is the Antichrist who sits in the Temple of God!</hi> But the Admonitions of these great Men were generally <hi>Songs unto the deaf;</hi> I say generally, because I cannot say universally: I do particularly know, that in the <hi>twelfth Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93774:11"/> there was a <hi>Treatise</hi> emitted in the name of some faithful Servants of Christ, concerning the <hi>Antichrist,</hi> which they said was then manifest in the <hi>Papacy;</hi> whereupon some did then sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. But the <hi>time for favor, the set time was not yet come!</hi> Indeed all this while our Lord Jesus Christ had his chaster Church, <hi>visibly</hi> existing among that <hi>chosen</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> Generation of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who, as <hi>Leger</hi> hath proved, were called <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denses,</hi> long before the time of <hi>Peter Valdo,</hi> which name (as they are now called <hi>Vandois</hi> from the word <hi>Vaux,</hi> that signifies a <hi>Vally</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd unto them, as inhabiting the <hi>Vallies</hi> of the <hi>Alps.</hi> From the sworn <hi>Enemies</hi> of that renowned People, we will briefly take their (therefore <hi>credible</hi>) Character and History. <hi>Claudius Sesselius</hi> the Archbishop of <hi>Turin,</hi> in a Book which he writ against the <hi>Waldenses,</hi> tells us, <hi>That the Sect of the</hi> Waldenses <hi>took its rise from a most religions Person, called</hi> Leo, <hi>that lived in the time of</hi> Constantine <hi>the Great, and who detesting the Covetousness of Pope</hi> Sylvester, <hi>and the immoderate Bounty of</hi> Constantine, <hi>chose rather to embrace Poverty with the simplicity of the Christian Faith, than with</hi> Sylvester <hi>to be defied with fat and rich Benefices; and that all they who were seriously Religious, joined themselves unto him. Reynerus Sacco</hi> the celebrated <hi>Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> quoted by the Jesuit <hi>Cretzer</hi> in his <hi>Biliothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> of the Fathers, has a like Passage; he says, <hi>Among all the Sects there is none that hath been so pernicious to the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>as that of the</hi> Leonists, <hi>because it is the most antient, and hath continued longest; for some affirm that it began in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93774:11"/> the time of</hi> Sylvester, <hi>and others in the time of the Apostles; and because they who are of it, have a great shew of Piety, live vertuously before Men, believe rightly of the Deity, and observe all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Creed.</hi> The Friar <hi>Belvedoras,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing the <hi>Missionaries</hi> for their not converting so much as one of the <hi>Waldenses,</hi> when they were sent among them, assigns this Reason for it; <hi>The Heresy is too firmly rooted there, for any to be able to do good among them; they of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys have been always, and through all times ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Hereticks.</hi> That sort of People call'd <hi>Waldenses,</hi> whose Errors, as <hi>Cascini</hi> the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciscan Friar declares, consisted in this, <hi>That they denied the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>to be the Holy Mother-Church, and would not obey her Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> These, for the condition they submitted unto, were call'd <hi>the Poor Men of</hi> Lions: In <hi>Dauphine,</hi> they were nicknamed <hi>Chaignards:</hi> From the Country of <hi>Albie,</hi> where their opinions much obtained, they were called <hi>Albigenses: Tramontani</hi> were those called that passed the <hi>Alps:</hi> In <hi>England</hi> they were called <hi>Lollards,</hi> from one <hi>Lollard,</hi> a chief Instructer of them there; and strict Laws were there made against the <hi>Conventicles</hi> of those that had this name applied unto them; [<hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether ever yet repeal'd?] In <hi>Italy</hi> they were called <hi>Fratricelli,</hi> or <hi>Men of the Brotherhood,</hi> from their <hi>brotherly</hi> way of living with one another: In <hi>Germany</hi> they were call'd <hi>Gazares,</hi> a word that carries the <hi>highest Cursedness</hi> and <hi>Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> in the signification of it: In <hi>Flanders</hi> they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93774:12"/> had the name of <hi>Turpelins,</hi> that is to say, <hi>Men dwelling with Wolves,</hi> because the heat of <hi>Persecution</hi> sometimes drove them to seek for quarters among the <hi>wild Beasts</hi> in the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness.</hi> This People were still disposed in sundry parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> with Circumstances no better than those which we have newly seen; Abbot <hi>Joachim,</hi> as their <hi>Quarter-Master,</hi> providing for them. They were always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised, always distressed, always under hatches: When they made any Figure, the bloody Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which cannot any more cease bloodily to persecute the Church of Christ, than the <hi>Leopard can change his Spots,</hi> quickly thundred out barbarous <hi>Croisados</hi> against them; in one of which <hi>Crosaidos</hi> alone, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himself with triumph relates, there were killed no less than an hundred thousand; and <hi>Perionius</hi> avers, that in <hi>France</hi> alone by one Persecution upon this People, there were no less than ten hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand murdered. When such terrible Dissipations were overwhelming the Churches of our Lord abroad, it pleased him in the <hi>fourteenth Century</hi> to bless our English Nation at home, with our memorable <hi>Wickliff,</hi> who sounded the alarm of <hi>Reformation</hi> louder than any that had been before him; he being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed especially by the Works of the godly and learned <hi>Robert Grosthead,</hi> set himself to decry the <hi>Pope</hi> as the very <hi>Antichrist;</hi> and that men might be rescued from the Snares of <hi>Popery,</hi> he not only <hi>preach'd</hi> and <hi>wrote</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the villanies of the <hi>Popish Clergy,</hi> but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93774:12"/> also translated the whole <hi>Bible</hi> into the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Language;</hi> whereby those Impressions were made on the minds of Men that never could be totally effaced. His very Adversaries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed themselves astonished at his <hi>Exercises</hi> and <hi>Abilities;</hi> none of the <hi>Bulls</hi> that roared from <hi>Rome</hi> against him, nor all the tricks of Papal Malice, at home, could prevent his dying peaceably in a good old Age at <hi>Lutterworth:</hi> the very name of which Town (signifying <hi>the Pure Word</hi>) hath in it a pleasant intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what this <hi>Town</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> was by <hi>Wickliff</hi> irradiated withal. But some of his followers, especially one <hi>Peter Payn,</hi> carried his <hi>Doctrines</hi> into <hi>Germany,</hi> where <hi>John Huss</hi> was thereby enlightened, and the <hi>Hussites</hi> began to grow considerable. Happy <hi>WICKLIFF!</hi> of whom, tho the mad Papists long after burnt his Bones, we will assign for an <hi>Epitaph,</hi> part of the <hi>Encomium</hi> which the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on <hi>Simon</hi> the Son of <hi>Onias: He was as the Morning-Star in the midst of a Cloud, and as a Rainbow diverting the fears of a Deluge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">§. 5. If <hi>Idolatry,</hi> if <hi>Heresy,</hi> if <hi>Cruelty</hi> could make a <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was now such a <hi>Babylon,</hi> that all who had any concern for their own everlasting Welfare, must think themselves concern'd now <hi>to come out of her;</hi> and it is well done of you, ye foolish <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi> to confess, that by <hi>Babylon</hi> the Oracles of Heaven intend <hi>Rome,</hi> when you go to prove <hi>Peter</hi>'s being at <hi>Rome</hi> from the Text
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93774:13"/> where you find him at <hi>Babylon;</hi> Sirs, <hi>Who hath bewitched you?</hi> Christianity was now so lost among the generality of them who wore the name of <hi>Christians,</hi> that their description may be given in the language of <hi>Bernard,</hi> one too far himself plunged in the general <hi>Apostacy, Religionis Antiquae non selum virtutem amiserunt, sed nec speciem retinent.</hi> Let us behold an <hi>Idea</hi> of the <hi>Apostacy!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Until the <hi>time of the Restitution of all things,</hi> 'tis the Gospel purely and plainly preached that must <hi>represent</hi> the Lord JESUS CHRIST unto the <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>joy</hi> of his People. But the <hi>Apostate Church,</hi> disliking such a spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Representation of our Lord, forbids Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to read the Scripture, and instead thereof <hi>ascends into Heaven</hi> to bring from thence <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of his heavenly Glory; <hi>descends into the Deep,</hi> to bring up <hi>Crucifixes</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> of his <hi>resurrection from the Dead;</hi> and they must have <hi>graven Images</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> that he may be nigh unto them; as the fond People of old had their <hi>Calf in the Wilderness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The real Beauty of Divine Worship lies in our devout <hi>homage</hi> to <hi>one God in three Persons,</hi> and our <hi>distinct respect</hi> unto <hi>each</hi> of those Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: But the <hi>Apostate Church,</hi> not beholding this Beauty, instead thereof set off their own Worship with an <hi>external Pomp,</hi> agreeable to carnal minds; <hi>meretricious Allurements,</hi> under the pretence of <hi>Decency,</hi> and all the <hi>Pageantry</hi> of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93774:13"/>
               <hi>Ceremonies, Vestments, Gestures, Musick, Painting,</hi> and <hi>beggarly Elements,</hi> Rites never instituted.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Believers are admitted unto a very pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and most intimate Communion with our Lord Redeemer, in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>holy Supper;</hi> A CHRIST suffering for us, is in that Sacrament, by the <hi>Symbols</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> so tendred unto the faithful, that in their <hi>obedience</hi> to his <hi>appointment</hi> of it, they do with ineffable advantage partake of him therein. But the <hi>Apostate Church,</hi> not having the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal experience of this matter, have in the room thereof, invented the sottish and horrid Monster of <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> with the <hi>Sacrifice of the Mass.</hi> They that could not <hi>bow down to this Image, have been cast into the fiery Furnace!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. There is a <hi>Catholick Church</hi> which is a <hi>Mystical Society,</hi> purchased and purified by the <hi>blood</hi> of the Lord Christ, and married unto him, and possessed by his Holy Spirit; part of this <hi>Family</hi> of God is, in conjunction with the holy Angels, arrived unto perfect Holiness in <hi>Heaven;</hi> part is on <hi>Earth,</hi> in the sure way unto it. But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> confines to it self the Notion of the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> it is a <hi>Society</hi> whereto not one inward and sincere Grace of Christianity is requisite; a visible profession of subjection to <hi>Romish Canons,</hi> is all that is required unto the Constitution of that <hi>Society;</hi> 'tis a wicked thing, by cursed Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments compounded for a secular Domination,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93774:14"/> that anathematizes all that conform not unto the Superstitions of it; and a <hi>Moloch</hi> which horribly devours the <hi>Children</hi> cast by the Ghostly Fathers into its devouring Flames.</p>
            <p n="5">V. The <hi>Churches</hi> true <hi>Glory</hi> lies in its <hi>Ʋnion</hi> to its Lord; his Presence with it, and Spirit in it; and its conformity and fidelity to his Laws alone: all the Gaities of this World are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to this Glory. But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> cannot see any comliness in the <hi>Spouse of Christ</hi> as adorned only with his Graces: in the place thereof they have brought in worldly <hi>Grandeurs, Dignities, Promotions;</hi> and the <hi>Glories of this World,</hi> which our Saviour would not accept at the <hi>Devil's hands,</hi> and on the <hi>Devil's Terms,</hi> in his Temptations, the Devil has proffer'd unto this Man of Sin, and he has accepted of them.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The <hi>Church</hi> is a Body which must have an Head, both for <hi>Influence</hi> and for <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> always present with it: And it is a wonder how Men could think of any other Head for this Body, besides the Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> without casting away their <hi>Bibles.</hi> But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> have set up another <hi>supream Head of the Church,</hi> even the <hi>Pope,</hi> the worst Idol that ever was heard of: One Pope re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scinds the Decrees of another, and it may be throws the Carcase of his Predecessor into the River; yea, <hi>Wretches</hi> which even their own Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries in their most allowed Histories call <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> and such as for their Diabolical Practices,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93774:14"/> yea, their explicit Covenants with <hi>Devils,</hi> and their being very <hi>Devils</hi> in Flesh, were confessed <hi>Ecclesiae opprobria,</hi> have been set up as the <hi>Vicars</hi> of Christ, the <hi>Centers</hi> of Unity, and the <hi>Husbands</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. The <hi>Discipline</hi> which our Lord has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Church to observe, must be such as to serve the Designs of <hi>Holiness,</hi> and shew unto Mankind the <hi>Love, Care</hi> and <hi>Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of the Lord himself towards the Church, and give a Testimony and <hi>Praeludium</hi> of his <hi>future Judgment;</hi> all of an <hi>Efficacy</hi> purely spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> in the lieu thereof, has erected a <hi>Discipline,</hi> consisting in a meer <hi>Tyranny</hi> over the Estates, the Liberties, the Lives of Men; a <hi>Tyranny</hi> managed with <hi>Weapons,</hi> which are <hi>mighty through the Devil,</hi> to destroy all that it falls upon; a <hi>Tyranny</hi> which by Courts, Fines, Mulcts, Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Capital Executions, hath made the Earth a <hi>Shambles,</hi> and been <hi>drunk with the Blood of Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII. The <hi>Disciples</hi> of our Lord own them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves obliged by him as far as they can, <hi>to disciple all Nations;</hi> They that have obtained <hi>precious Faith,</hi> must as they are able, <hi>propagate the Faith;</hi> Nevertheless, 'tis only the diligent and patient, and uncorrupt preaching of the Gospel, by which the <hi>Gospel would run and be glorified.</hi> But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> dislikes this <hi>primitive way</hi> of proselyting Mankind unto the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93774:15"/> of the Gospel: A <hi>Congregatio de propagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dâ side,</hi> with a vast crue of <hi>Missionaries</hi> from the overstockt <hi>Fraternities,</hi> is continually employed for the gaining of Proselytes; but by what Methods? truly by Fire and Sword, and bloody Murders and Massacres, like those which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> committed upon the poor <hi>Indians,</hi> when the Children of <hi>Cain</hi> butcher'd more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents in <hi>America,</hi> than some think there are People alive at any one time in <hi>Europe:</hi> or by the <hi>Inquisition,</hi> a thing that can't be painted, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out first besmearing, as the exact Painter for that purpose once did it, the Table with Blood; a meer <hi>Cacus</hi>'s Den, the horriblest <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senal</hi> of Cruelty that ever was upon the face of the Earth; or finally, by Seditions, Rebellions, Conspiracies, the embroiling of Nations, and subverting their fundamental Constitutions, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>snaring wretched Persons, first into <hi>Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> so into <hi>Atheism,</hi> then into <hi>Indigency,</hi> that they may an last be taken in the Snares of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. 'Tis a principle of our blessed Religion, that God the <hi>Sovereign Lord</hi> of all things, is to be obeyed <hi>absolutely</hi> and <hi>universally:</hi> His Will is to be the highest Reason of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> has superceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this, by imposing upon Men a <hi>Vow of blind Obedience to their Superiors,</hi> urging for that Vow the Example of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Obedience: And thus all the Interests of Men lie at the Mercies of a spurious Offspring, the most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93774:15"/> Dregs of Mankind, who are nourished up to be the <hi>Janisaries</hi> of the <hi>Papal Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. The Nature of Man is polluted by Sin, and the pollution must be taken away before Men can enter into the <hi>Kingdom of God;</hi> nor can any thing but the Blood of the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ the Son of God, cleansing us from all our Sins,</hi> take it away. But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns not the sweetness of this <hi>Mystery,</hi> the <hi>Blood of the Son of God</hi> applied unto the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> to purge it from dead works: the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Fopperies of <hi>Holy Water,</hi> of <hi>Pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> of <hi>Disciplines,</hi> of <hi>Masses,</hi> and various <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutations,</hi> were employed as <hi>Purgations of Sin;</hi> and when they found that these things would neither purify nor pacify the <hi>Conscience,</hi> they feigned a certain <hi>subterraneous Purgatory,</hi> where the Souls of Men were by exquisite Afflictions made meet for <hi>Heaven;</hi> and their <hi>Venial Sins,</hi> which they make the most, are capable of an <hi>Expiation</hi> after this life, tho there were no <hi>Repentance</hi> in it; and this Fiction they placed behind the Curtain of <hi>Mortality,</hi> that so no man living might find out the <hi>Cheat:</hi> and thus adding an imaginary <hi>Store-house</hi> of <hi>Ecclesiastical Merits,</hi> the Keys whereof are committed unto that great <hi>Adulterer</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> they have cheated Nations of Riches far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Revenues of Emperors.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. All our help against the <hi>Flesh,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and our Deliverance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93774:16"/> from all evil, is in our Lord Jesus Christ alone; who by his Death on the <hi>Cross,</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased all this Good for us; and it is by <hi>Faith</hi> in him, that we bespeak and enjoy the actual Communication of it. But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> only makes the sign of the <hi>Cross,</hi> instead of an Application to him who died on it: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Virtues do they ascribe unto this cursed Idol.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. They that approach unto God, should be in all holiness free from <hi>offensive Defilements.</hi> But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> hath to this end bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the old <hi>Pagans,</hi> the ludicrous Trifles of sprinkling all with holy Water, that they may be holy.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. That our Souls may live, the death of our Sins is necessary; and it is in the Destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Extinction of our <hi>vitious Habits,</hi> by the Spirit of Christ crucified, in the daily Duties of <hi>laborious Devotion,</hi> that we have our necessary <hi>Mortification.</hi> But the <hi>Apostate Church</hi> has prescribed <hi>Monastical</hi> Retirements, Penances, and Self-Macerations, not pleasing unto God, but highly pleasing to the <hi>Daemons</hi> in Chains, whose delight it is to see Men also in <hi>Chains of Darkness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Good Works, tho utterly excluded from any share in the Justification of Sinners, are yet indispensably needful to the present and future Comfort of <hi>Believers.</hi> But the <hi>Apostate
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93774:16"/> Church,</hi> pretending to perform good Works from their own Free-will, do advance the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence unto the vain pride of <hi>Merit</hi> in them; yea they carry on the <hi>Merit,</hi> even to a <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererrogation.</hi> Such Protestant Pens as our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>Owen</hi>'s, have abundantly stated these points of the <hi>grand Apostacy.</hi> I think I have now recited no less than <hi>twice seven Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> of that woful <hi>Apostacy,</hi> whereinto the Church in the <hi>Western</hi> part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was precipitated, while at the same time the Church in the <hi>Eastern</hi> part of the Empire fell under the <hi>Mahometan Oppressions</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions.</hi> And now
<q xml:lang="lat">Qui Satanam non odit, amet tua Dogmata, Papa!</q> But is not here enough to anticipate the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions of my Reader, that the truest and furthest Recovery out of the <hi>Romish Apostacy</hi> hitherto seen, is that which they that go by the Name of <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> in the <hi>English Nation,</hi> have endeavoured? And that it is not possible for the Church to recover effectually out of this <hi>Apostacy,</hi> without acting upon such <hi>Principles</hi> as have at last produced in the <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican</hi> Desarts, a whole Nation of <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">§. 6. Till the TIME, and the TIMES of <hi>Antichrist</hi> had rolled away, the call to <hi>come out of Babylon</hi> could not become effectual unto the Nations that were under the <hi>Babylonish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxications;</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93774:17"/> but when the last HALF TIME of an <hi>hundred and eighty</hi> years, left for the Reign of this <hi>Antichrist,</hi> was entring, it was <hi>high time</hi> for our Lord JESUS CHRIST, then to make some reprisal of that <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Which at the time of the end, shall <hi>under the whole Heaven be given to the People of the Saints of the Most High.</hi> Then it was, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Prophecies uttered by the two <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian Martyrs</hi> an hundred years before, must receive their accomplishment; and the People who had been too long <hi>fleec'd,</hi> yea, <hi>flay'd</hi> by the Tyrannies of <hi>Rome,</hi> grew willing to pare the Talons of the <hi>Ecclesiastical Harpies. Behold how great a Matter a little Fire kindles!</hi> In the year 1617, Pope <hi>Leo</hi> X. under a pretence of War against the <hi>Turk,</hi> sent abroad his Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, promising the Pardons of Sins to all that would give Mony for them; and among the <hi>Hacksters</hi> of these <hi>Pardons,</hi> was one <hi>Tece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> a Dominican Friar, of whom <hi>Lonicerus</hi> writes, <hi>Pontificis dignitatem &amp; potentiam, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiarumque virtutem &amp; efficaciam impudenter praedicabat;</hi> yea, he adds, The Man kept bawling, that there could be no wickedness committed, so great, but it might be forgiven by these Indulgences; and that the Souls tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> as soon as the Mony <hi>[ten Shillings]</hi> was flung into the Bason, skipt for Joy, and being released from their Pains, flew up to Heaven. <hi>MARTIN LƲTHER,</hi> one born at <hi>Isleben</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi> and now a Monk in the Order of St. <hi>Augustin,</hi> and a Professor of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93774:17"/> at <hi>Wittemberg,</hi> but a Person illuminated in the Article of <hi>Justification,</hi> by the private Conferences and Expositions of an honest old Monk on <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epistles, began to oppose the impudent <hi>Cheats</hi> and <hi>Shams</hi> which these <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> imposed on the People. He first wrote Letters to the Archbishop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and the Bishop of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint of these Abuses; the neglect of which Letters egg'd him on to publish <hi>Propositions,</hi> which exasperated the business, till he had been made a Sacrifice unto the <hi>Papal Fury,</hi> if the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> then upon the Death of the Emperor, the <hi>Vicar of the Empire,</hi> had not been so moved by his powerful Preaching, as to abet him, and assist him in his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings. This was that famous <hi>Luther,</hi> of whom they that will acknowledg the least, must yet come to as much acknowledgment as Dr. <hi>More</hi> makes of him: <q rend="margDblQuotes">I cannot think so very highly of <hi>Luther</hi> as some do (saith he) and yet I think him to have been a very <hi>happy Instrument</hi> in the hand of God, for the good of <hi>Christendom,</hi> against the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Enormities of the <hi>Papal Hierarchy.</hi> And tho he might not be allowed to be the <hi>Elias,</hi> the <hi>Conducter</hi> and <hi>Chariot</hi> of <hi>Israel,</hi> (as some have stiled him,) yet I think at least he might be accounted a faithful <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilion</hi> in that <hi>Chariot,</hi> who was well accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with his Wax <hi>Boots,</hi> oiled <hi>Coat</hi> and <hi>Hood,</hi> and who turned the Horses <hi>Noses</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a direct way from <hi>Babylon</hi> toward the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93774:18"/>
                  <hi>City of God,</hi> and held on in a <hi>good round trot</hi> thro <hi>thick and thin</hi> not eating to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatter others in this <hi>High Fog,</hi> as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was finely bespattered by others.</q> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the very <hi>same time,</hi> or about a year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, did <hi>Zuinglius</hi> appear at <hi>Zurich</hi> in <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> against the like Abominations of <hi>Popery;</hi> nor could all the <hi>Compliments</hi> and <hi>Enchantments,</hi> with offers of <hi>Preferments</hi> from the Pontifical Chair, bribe him into <hi>silence;</hi> but he went on, till the <hi>Evangelical Truth</hi> was far and near embraced. Long would be our work, to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eidan,</hi> and relate the Actions of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> that accompanied <hi>Luther,</hi> and of <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampadius</hi> that accompanied <hi>Zuinglius</hi> in the <hi>Reformation;</hi> or so much as to recite the <hi>Names</hi> of the more than <hi>thirty Worthies,</hi> who were by the marvellous Providence of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, raised up to act great parts in this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Revolution;</hi> and who had no secular En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, but bravely denied and renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>rich Livings,</hi> and encountred with the <hi>Cross</hi> in all its mortifications, for the sake of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> and were not unwilling to die, as well as to live, under the Circumstances particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly related concerning some of them intes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, <hi>Quià undè conderet, pauper Christi servus, non habebat:</hi> Only because the Name of CALVIN, a Person to be reckon'd one of the <hi>first three,</hi> is unaccountably, since the <hi>Tares</hi> of <hi>Arminius</hi> have been so cherished, become an Object of scorn and hate, among a Generation of mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queraded Enemies to the <hi>Reformation,</hi> who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93774:18"/> arrogate unto themselves the stile of <hi>The Church of</hi> England, I may not leave that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable name unmention'd, but I must men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it with an Account of the Veneration, which the <hi>old Church of</hi> England paid unto it, when Dr. <hi>Carlton</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> in a Book dedicated unto K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>Anno</hi> 1626. thus wrote; <q rend="margDblQuotes">As for <hi>Calvin,</hi> his Name and Doctrines are made odious; but why, I know not. Some take it for a sign of <hi>looking towards Popery,</hi> when the Members of our own Church offer such a service to the <hi>Papists,</hi> as to speak evil of them that have been the greatest Enemies to Popery, the greatest Propugnators of the Truth:</q> And when Dr. <hi>Hakewel,</hi> Chaplain to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> in a Book dedicated unto K. <hi>James</hi> I. <hi>Anno</hi> 1616, wrote thus: <q rend="margDblQuotes">One of the main points you drive at, is to put us off from all fellowship and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with those Churches, who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg <hi>Calvin</hi> to have been an <hi>excellent Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God,</hi> in abolishing and suppressing of <hi>Popery,</hi> and the clearing and spreading of his Truth; and so through <hi>Calvin</hi>'s sides you <hi>strike at the Throat and Heart of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
               </q> And when Dr. <hi>Hoyl,</hi> a judicious Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in a Book dedicated unto Archbishop <hi>Ʋsher,</hi> as being written by his direction, wrote after this manner; <q rend="margDblQuotes">That great Instrument of God's Glory, <hi>John Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> was a Man of whom I had almost said, as once it was of <hi>Moses, That there arose not a Prophet since like him</hi> in <hi>Israel,</hi> nor
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93774:19"/> since the Apostles days <hi>was before him.</hi> His works shall praise him for Wit, Eloquence, Fulness and Soundness of Divinity, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and multitude, advanc'd among the highest, that the World may justly admire, how they could be so many, being so good; and so good, being so many.</q>
               <hi>And much more to this purpose, too much to be in this place repeated,</hi> concerning this incomparable Man; the first line of whose <hi>Epitaph,</hi> at last gave him his true commendation: <hi>Romae ruentis Terror ille maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> As for the common Cavil of our <hi>Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palians,</hi> that <hi>Calvin</hi> was he who rebelliously ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> the Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate of the City, 'tis as true as <hi>Heylins</hi> Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy of that City. Let not me, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Author, Dr. <hi>Henry More,</hi> assure the Reader that the Bishop fled away eight months before <hi>Calvin</hi>'s coming, being <hi>hated by the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> for the <hi>Rape of a Virgin,</hi> and many <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries with their Wives,</hi> and in fear of his life for his Conspiracy with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> to oppress the Liberties of the City, for which his Secretary was hanged; and they who changed the <hi>Government</hi> were <hi>strong Papists,</hi> and afterwards main Opposers of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> But I hasten to observe, that when <hi>Angels</hi> thus <hi>flew</hi> thro the <hi>midst of Heaven,</hi> preaching the <hi>everlasting Gospel,</hi> so quick was the Progress of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> and so wonderful its <hi>Conquest,</hi> and its <hi>Triumph,</hi> as to fill half of <hi>Europe</hi> in less than forty years, with <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> which from a <hi>Protestation</hi> made by several
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93774:19"/> States, that were zealous for the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> against the Decrees of a Popish Diet, in the year 1526, have been ever since called PROTESTANTS: A Progress of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantism,</hi> which at length caused <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> to confess and complain, That <hi>Heresy</hi> now possessed almost all <hi>Germany, Denmark, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Sweedland, Gothia, Hungary, France, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> the <hi>Low Countries, Polonia, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, Helvetia,</hi> and it was got over the <hi>Alps</hi> into <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time was now come that the <hi>ten Kings</hi> must begin to <hi>hate the Whore</hi> that had bewitched them; which <hi>Hatred</hi> was very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly exemplified by K. <hi>James</hi> V. of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> when the Popish <hi>Prelates</hi> were advising him to destroy his Nobles and Barons that were Friends unto the <hi>Reformation: Wherefore</hi> (said he, as 'tis related by that rare Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Sir <hi>James Melvil) did my Predecessors give so many Lands and Rents to the Kirk? Was it to maintain Hawks, Dogs and Whores to a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of idle Priests? The King of</hi> England <hi>hangs you; the King</hi> Denmark <hi>beheads you; and I will stick you with this Whingar!</hi> Whereupon he drew out his Dagger, and they fled out of his Presence.</p>
            <p>'Tis observ'd that, in the <hi>first Song</hi> that any Writings have recorded or mentioned, even that of <hi>Moses,</hi> many words are put in the <hi>future Tense,</hi> and the very first words are, <hi>Then SHALL sing</hi> Moses. I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that from this very Remark the <hi>Jewish
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93774:20"/> Rabbins</hi> hence inferr'd the Doctrine of the <hi>Resurrection;</hi> and there are <hi>Christian Writers,</hi> who hence infer that the Song looks not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>backward,</hi> on the deliverance of the Church from <hi>Egypt,</hi> but also <hi>forward,</hi> on the deliverance of the Church from that worse than <hi>Egyptian,</hi> even the <hi>Antichristian</hi> Yoke in the latter days. Truly, the Church now was beginning to get out from the <hi>Sea,</hi> where tho they had been tortured with <hi>Fire,</hi> yet they had hitherto been detained with impassable Flakes of <hi>Ice</hi> over their Heads: The Church now therefore began to <hi>sing the Song of</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses <hi>the Servant of God, and Heaven</hi> eccho'd unto the Melody: And now
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>—Non ultra tolerare potest Ecclesia porcos,</l>
                  <l>Duntaxat ventri, veneri, somnoque vacantes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="7">§. 7. When the antient <hi>Babylon</hi> was to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, way was to be made for it, as the Sacred Oracles foretold, <hi>By the drying up of her Waters;</hi> and <hi>Xenophon,</hi> as well as others, reports to us, how wonderfully <hi>Cyrus</hi> fulfilled what was foretold, when he made his Passage to <hi>Babylon,</hi> by turning the <hi>Euphrataan Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> into another Channel. Then it was not long before her <hi>broad Walls</hi> [fifty Cubits broad, saith <hi>Herodotus] were broken down, and her high Gates</hi> [two hundred Cubits high, saith <hi>Strabo] were burnt with Fire.</hi> Truly, the <hi>Reformation</hi> thus begun, did wonderfully
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93774:20"/> turn the Waters of our Mystical <hi>Babylon</hi> into another Channel; whole Nations of <hi>People</hi> were turned another way: And this prepares that <hi>Babylon</hi> for the approaching day; when <hi>Babylon shall become a Desolation among the Nations, and she shall become a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mountain,</hi> overthrown <hi>as God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah.</hi> But the <hi>Antichrist</hi> had yet an <hi>half-time</hi> to reign; and therefore no wonder if but <hi>half-work</hi> were done in the <hi>separation</hi> then made from him. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, the <hi>Reformation</hi> which was no where ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>perfect,</hi> had in several Nations, various degrees of its <hi>perfection;</hi> some went much further than others in restoring of <hi>Primitive Christianity,</hi> and reforming of all things, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>word of Christ.</hi> In this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, very particular and remarkable was the Condition of <hi>England,</hi> where the best part of the <hi>Reformers</hi> who began the Work in the days of King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. on Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and in Manners well known to the World, and carried it on in the days of K. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. did really desire to pursue it as far as they should see <hi>light</hi> for it in the Sacred <hi>Scripture,</hi> the only Rule of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> but there was always a corrupt, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Party,</hi> who being jealous of too far a Secession from <hi>Rome,</hi> did resolve still to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at least so much of the <hi>Romish Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> as might gratify their Aims at a <hi>worldly Domination</hi> in the Church of God. All the World hath long since been informed,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93774:21"/> that in the year 1554. a number of conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Protestants,</hi> flying from the bloody storm of <hi>Persecution,</hi> with which the miserable Queen <hi>Mary</hi> for a while retarded and confounded the <hi>Reformation,</hi> that the Reign of her ever glorious Brother had so far advanced, were kindly entertain'd at <hi>Frankford;</hi> and when those Holy Men pursued that <hi>Reformation</hi> so far, as to leave out of their Worship those unhappy <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which they perceived likely to prove <hi>scandalous</hi> unto the <hi>purer Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> of God, several Men that were furiously zealous for the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> did with all pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible fury disturb them in their Proceedings. This renowned Congregation of <hi>Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> then wrote unto <hi>Zurick</hi> in their own Vindication, such memorable words as these: <q rend="margDblQuotes">As touching the <hi>substance</hi> of the Book <hi>[of Common Prayer]</hi> we desire the observation of it <hi>so far as God's Word commands.</hi> But for the <hi>unprofitable Ceremonies,</hi> they are not to be used. Surely it were better they should never be <hi>practised,</hi> than that they should prove the <hi>subversion of our Church,</hi> which would be much hazarded by the use of them. If any think that the not using the Book in <hi>all points,</hi> will tend to the dishonor of the Laws of our late Sovereign of famous Memory King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. he seems little to weigh the matter; or else, hindred by Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norances, knoweth not, that even <hi>they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves upon consideration of Circumstances, have altered many things, and if God had not in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93774:21"/> these wicked days prevented, would have altered more:</hi> and we doubt not but in our case they would have done the like.</q> Those great Men, Mr. <hi>Knox,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whittingham,</hi> composed a <hi>Directory</hi> for the Congregation, like that of <hi>Geneva;</hi> and <hi>Knox</hi> preached, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That by the <hi>word of God</hi> we must seek our <hi>warrant</hi> for the establishing of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> without which <hi>warrant</hi> nothing is to be obtruded upon <hi>Christians;</hi> and that in the <hi>English Service-Book</hi> there were <hi>supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> and <hi>impure,</hi> and <hi>imperfect</hi> things; and that the <hi>slackness in Reforming Religion</hi> when there was an Opportunity, was one of the many things whereby God's Anger against <hi>England</hi> had been provoked; and that whereas there were some not <hi>ashamed to say,</hi> that <hi>Reformation was perfected</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the contrary was proved in the <hi>want of a good Discipline,</hi> which appeared by the Troubles that good Master <hi>Hooper</hi> had sustained in the time of King <hi>Edward.</hi>
               </q> But by the infamous <hi>Bigotry</hi> of Dr. <hi>Cox</hi> and his Associates, <hi>conformity</hi> to the scrupled <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> was pressed at such a rate, that the oppressed Congregation was driven away unto <hi>Basil</hi> and <hi>Geneva;</hi> and the <hi>Prelatical party</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented not themselves, without seeking the very <hi>Blood</hi> of Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> by an accusation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd against him; an <hi>Accusation</hi> so barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and inhumane, that the <hi>Magistrates</hi> of the City to whom it was brought, expressed their abhorrence of it; howbeit, his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93774:22"/> was thereby occasioned. If now there were inscribed on the Graves of these Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons <hi>[In their Coffins here now lie shut up, they that first open'd the true PANDORA'S Box in the English Nation]</hi> it would be a stroke less liable to contestation, than that <hi>Popish</hi> one, which afterwards in Dr. <hi>Coxes</hi> Epitaph, gave such <hi>scandal</hi> as to be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished. Reader, In these troubles at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> there was the <hi>Epitome,</hi> and in some sort the <hi>Original</hi> of the struggles about <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> both <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> which have ever since distressed the Church of God in the English Nation: until at length a <hi>new England</hi> was found out, as a <hi>refuge from the storm</hi> of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptural <hi>Impositions</hi> urged with unnatural <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions.</hi> From the very beginning of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> there hath always been a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Godly Men, desirous to pursue the <hi>Reformation of Religion, in Doctrine, Worship, Discipline and Government, according to the word of God, and the example of the best Reformed Churches:</hi> and there hath been another Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Men who have employed the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> which they have still generally had in their hands, not only to <hi>stop</hi> the progress of the desired <hi>Reformation,</hi> but also with innumerable vexations to persecute those that were the most hearty friends unto it. All Mankind knows that among those who jointly forsook the <hi>Papacy,</hi> there were <hi>different apprehensions</hi> about the <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> to be maintain'd in the Church; and we have no <hi>Record</hi> of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93774:22"/> any <hi>attempt</hi> for the healing of these <hi>differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> before there was by <hi>Law established</hi> one certain <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Order;</hi> which thro the pertinacious adherency not only of <hi>most People</hi> unto their <hi>old ways,</hi> but even of the <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> the greatest part of whom disliked the <hi>whole Reformation;</hi> and through the extreme scarcity of <hi>able Minis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> underwent as little alteration from the former Usages as was possible. This <hi>Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of things was very dissatisfactory to very many of the <hi>best Men</hi> in the Land; who yet considering the <hi>necessity of the Times,</hi> did more or less acquiesce in it, hoping and plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the <hi>Reformation</hi> might proceed in <hi>due time</hi> unto more of <hi>Purity:</hi> but they that found their own <hi>secular Interests</hi> accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated in this <hi>Constitution,</hi> set themselves after a while to fine, silence, deprive, censure, and imprison those that were dissatisfied, and <hi>smite their Fellow-Servants,</hi> who remained in <hi>privacy</hi> under their Sufferings, waiting still for more of <hi>Reformation. Thus</hi> Edom <hi>refused to give</hi> Israel <hi>passage through his Border, wherefore</hi> Israel <hi>turned away from him!</hi> After some years of a fruitless <hi>expectation,</hi> the severities which were multiplied upon them drove mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes unto a more open <hi>separation</hi> from the things that were by <hi>Law established:</hi> a <hi>sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> which yet was opposed by others that also passionately longed and even groaned for a <hi>National Reformation.</hi> Tho not being wholly agreed among themselves about the <hi>measure</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93774:23"/> of <hi>Separation</hi> or of <hi>Reformation</hi> to be attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto, there insued several Inconveniencies thereupon which had no little <hi>Temptation</hi> in them. <hi>Then</hi> 'twas, that, as our great <hi>Owen</hi> has expressed it, <hi>Multitudes of pious, peaceable Protestants were driven by their Severities to leave their Native Country, and seek a Refuge for their Lives and Liberties, with freedom for the worship of God in a Wilderness, in the ends of the Earth.</hi> There are none that more heartily bless God for the <hi>first Reformers,</hi> and for the service they did in the <hi>Reformation,</hi> or that more firmly cleave to their <hi>Doctrine</hi> which was the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> than these <hi>Non-conformists</hi> have ever done, or that more try to follow them in their <hi>noble design.</hi> But, as those <hi>first Reformers</hi> never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that what <hi>they</hi> did should be the <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute boundary</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> from whence it were a sin to dissent or depart, which would have been to have only changed <hi>one Popery</hi> for another, and quite contrary to their own going beyond <hi>Wickliff,</hi> and <hi>changing</hi> and <hi>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in their own <hi>models</hi> also, and the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Confessions of the great <hi>Cranmer</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, who <hi>fatchatur multa detracta oportere superflua, &amp; ardentibus votis cupiebat ea in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius correcta;</hi> And the Orders of King <hi>Edward</hi> unto <hi>Bucer,</hi> to write for further Amendments, whom accordingly we find in his Learned <hi>Scripta Anglicana</hi> doing so; thus the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> have been willing to imitate them in exercising that <hi>Liberty wherewith Christ hath
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93774:23"/> made them free.</hi> This is very sure, that those very <hi>Principles</hi> upon which the <hi>first Reformers</hi> built the <hi>Reformation,</hi> are those that have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and justified the hundreds of thousands of <hi>Non-conformists</hi> which have so long asked for further steps to be taken in it; namely those <hi>Principles,</hi> that the Word of our Lord Jesus Christ is a <hi>perfect Rule</hi> of all that we are to believe or practise in <hi>Religion:</hi> and, that <hi>Christian People</hi> not being tied up to the blind obedience of their <hi>Ecclesiastical Guides,</hi> are to judg <hi>for themselves</hi> what they are to believe or to practise in <hi>Religion.</hi> 'Tis very sure also, that the <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Challenge made by Dr. <hi>Jewel,</hi> one of our first <hi>Reformers,</hi> unto the <hi>Romish</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, upon their unjust imputation of <hi>Novelty</hi> unto the <hi>Reformation,</hi> have published a <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge</hi> in such Terms as these.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">If any <hi>Learned Man</hi> of our Adversaries, be able to bring any one sufficient Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence out of the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> or any one Example of any <hi>Bishop, Minister,</hi> or (afterwards) <hi>Martyr</hi> in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, or in the times of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> any passage out of Bishop <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> which do directly and, <hi>ex professo,</hi> plead for, and commend the present <hi>Liturgy</hi> in the frame of it, or assert that <hi>Episcopacy</hi> is <hi>Jure-Divino,</hi> or argue for Adoration to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Altar,</hi> bowing at the name of <hi>Jesus,</hi> signing with the sign of the <hi>Cross,</hi> wearing of the <hi>Surplice,</hi> kneeling at the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93774:24"/>
                  <hi>Sacrament,</hi> or for the exercise of <hi>Church-power</hi> by <hi>Lay Chancellors,</hi> we will then <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> and <hi>subscribe.</hi>
               </q> And none hath answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</p>
            <p n="8">§. 8. If the Reader will accept the Report and Judgment of a <hi>Non-conformist,</hi> concerning the condition of the Church in the <hi>English Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at the time of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> it must be thus. The God of Heaven having sent the light of the <hi>Gospel</hi> into the Minds of the <hi>King</hi> and some that were his chief Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, disposing them to the <hi>Reformation,</hi> they found it a business incredibly difficult for them to incounter the inveterate and incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable prejudices with which Mankind were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally possessed, against the work by them desired and intended. The greatest part of the greater Men, the <hi>Nobles</hi> and the <hi>Gentry,</hi> were averse to the proceedings of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers;</hi> the most of the <hi>Clergy</hi> were so true unto their own carnal Interests, that with <hi>might</hi> and <hi>main</hi> they opposed those Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and the body of the <hi>People</hi> horribly blinded with Superstition and Prophanity, were easily <hi>Priest-ridden,</hi> to join with their <hi>blind Leaders</hi> in their troublesom oppositions: Nor were the Nations in the Neighbourhood left uninstigated by the <hi>Pope,</hi> to foment the discontents of the People on this occasion. The body of the People were those which in these difficulties the King most of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, knowing, that they were his <hi>Wealth</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93774:24"/> and <hi>Strength,</hi> and that without <hi>their</hi> concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Dissatisfactions of all others would hurt none but themselves. Now the People in those days being miserably unacquainted with the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Scripture, were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little or nothing at all concerned, what perswasions Men held in matters of pure <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> provided they might retain those <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Modes</hi> in their <hi>Worship,</hi> whereto they had been accustomed. Accordingly we know, that the <hi>Prelates</hi> who carried on the <hi>Papal Persecution</hi> against the <hi>Reformers,</hi> rarely, if ever, unless compelled by Disputations, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the <hi>Opinions</hi> about the <hi>Credenda</hi> of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as the grounds of the Quarrel, tho these were the <hi>main grounds</hi> of all; because the <hi>common People</hi> would not have been easily prevailed withal, to bring in Faggots for the burning of their Brethren on those more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struse accounts: but it was in the <hi>agenda</hi> of <hi>Worship,</hi> that they wisely stated the cause of all their Cruelty, because they saw that the <hi>common People</hi> would violently interpose on the behalf of the <hi>Mass,</hi> wherein their <hi>share of Religion</hi> chiefly lay.</p>
            <p>Our considerate <hi>Reformers,</hi> considering the disposition of the <hi>People,</hi> first of all, with a brave Resolution, asserted the true <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Gospel, and renounced the Errors and Follies with which the <hi>Antichristian Apostacy</hi> had envenom'd it: but then they <hi>attempered</hi> the way of public <hi>Worship</hi> as far as ever the Articles of their <hi>Faith</hi> would permit them
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93774:25"/>
               <hi>(if no further)</hi> unto that which the <hi>Populace</hi> had been us'd unto. It was a thing very sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible unto them, that so long as ths People were accommodated with as much conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as might be unto their former <hi>customs</hi> in <hi>Divine Service,</hi> the main <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> which ('twas hop'd) would at length introduce a <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Worship</hi> also, might go on with less <hi>Observation,</hi> and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with less <hi>Contestation.</hi> And the Priests find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>provision</hi> thus made for their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the possession of their Places, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing further prescribed, but what was as easy to be performed as any thing that had been practised in former days, would quietly let their betters go on with what they had undertaken. On these considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the English <hi>Liturgy</hi> was formed, and the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> thus composed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came from the very beginning a <hi>bone of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> in the Church of God. Many that were inlightned with such <hi>rays</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> as had irradiated the chief Instruments of the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> utterly decried this compliance with the ignorance and vanity of the <hi>People,</hi> and cried out earnestly for <hi>purer Administrations</hi> of <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Ordinances,</hi> agreeable to the word of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the examples of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christianity;</hi> whilst others would not hear of going any farther than that <hi>first Essay</hi> of <hi>Reformation.</hi> Only, a <hi>long experience</hi> hath made it evident, that the more the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the <hi>Gospel</hi> hath increased in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93774:25"/> the more hath increased the dislike of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and its Appurtenances: nor can the <hi>Liturgy</hi> with its unscriptural and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <hi>Discipline,</hi> be secured, without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of hundreds of thousands of as good <hi>Christians</hi> as any in the Land, yea, and of the very <hi>Bibles</hi> that have made them so; which, if any are so wicked as to imagine, let them know, <hi>Aliter statutum est in coelo!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>Reader!</hi> because it is a <hi>lubricous</hi> and a <hi>difficult</hi> Theme which we are now upon, thou shalt not have my <hi>Sense</hi> of these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters imposed upon thee; I will carry thee with me to more significant and sufficient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, even those <hi>Historians</hi> who were no <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> but liv'd and dy'd in the fullest <hi>Conformity</hi> to the <hi>Rites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>by Law established;</hi> and thou shalt have thy choice to take thy informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either from an Historian, that was an enemy to any <hi>further progress</hi> of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> or from an Historian to whom such a progress in the <hi>Reformation</hi> as the first mover thereof design'd, would not have been so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasteful; that is to say, either from an <hi>HEY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIN,</hi> or from a <hi>FƲLLER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let a bitter <hi>HEYLIN,</hi> in his <hi>History of the Reformation of the Church of</hi> England, be consulted, and he will tell us;</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:93774:26"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> he cannot reckon the Death of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, for an infelicity to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> not to <hi>press too much at once upon the People,</hi> it was thought fit to smooth the way to the <hi>Reformation,</hi> by setting out some <hi>preparatory Injunctions;</hi> all which was done to this intent, that the People in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being prepared by little and little, might with more Ease and less Opposition, admit the <hi>total Alteration, which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in due time to be introduced.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> some godly Bishops and other Learned and Religious Men (the same that made the <hi>Liturgy</hi>) were imployed in the Castle of <hi>Windsor</hi> by the King's Command, to consult about one <hi>uniform Order,</hi> for the administring of the Holy Communion; and they agreed on such a <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> as might comply with the intention of the King and Parliament, without giving any just offence to the <hi>Romish</hi> Party.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> the <hi>Liturgy</hi> being finished, accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and enacted, gave great offence to the <hi>Romish Party,</hi> not that they could except against it, in regard either of the matter or the manner of it, but because it was communicated to the People in the <hi>vulgar Tongue.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:93774:26"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> then <hi>Calvin</hi> and his followers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the King and Council to a further <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> when Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> came to the Crown, she retained such as had been of Privy-Council unto Queen <hi>Mary</hi> (her Sister) to be of her Council. And in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, which altered, and again imposed the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer,</hi> great care was taken for expunging all such Passages in it as might give any Scandal or Offence to the <hi>Popish</hi> party. And tho by <hi>Calvin</hi>'s means, some <hi>Reformation</hi> had been made in the second <hi>Liturgy,</hi> in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time, now it is returned back into the first Form, and by <hi>compliances,</hi> the <hi>Book</hi> was made so passable among the <hi>Papists,</hi> that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired unto our <hi>Parish-Churches</hi> without scruple.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> what was done in the form of our Devotions, did so far satisfy the <hi>Pope</hi> then being, that he shewed himself willing to <hi>confirm all</hi> by his <hi>Papal Power;</hi> and that <hi>Parpalio</hi> was instructed to offer in the name of his Holiness, <hi>That the English Liturgy should be confirmed.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> things abolished by King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, and revived by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> were by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> retain'd as formerly in her Father's time; for which she receiv'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93774:27"/> both thanks and honor from her very E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; that is to say, <hi>the Papists.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> in the beginning of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> Reign, many that were disaffected un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Episcopacy</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> were raised unto great Preferment; and even the Queens-Professor at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the <hi>Margaret</hi>-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> were <hi>Non-conformists.</hi>
               </q> These and many more such things as these are affirmed, by that <hi>Heylin,</hi> who, tho for his <hi>Divinity,</hi> the most Reverend Archbishop <hi>Ʋsher</hi> says, <hi>He had need be put to learn his Catechism again;</hi> and for his <hi>Geography,</hi> the same Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop says, <hi>He deserves little credit, when he brings us news from the remote parts of the World, that tells us so many untruths of things publickly acted in his neighbour Nation:</hi> Yet in these Paragraphs of his <hi>History,</hi> is incontes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>But how let us consult a better, <hi>FƲL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LER;</hi> and <hi>he,</hi> in his <hi>Church-History of</hi> Britain, will tell us:</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> as careful Mothers and Nurses, on condition they can get their Children to part with <hi>Knives,</hi> are contented to let them play with <hi>Rattles;</hi> thus the <hi>Reformers</hi> permitted ignorant People still to retain some of their fond and foolish <hi>Customs,</hi> that they might remove from them the most dangerous and destructive <hi>Superstitions.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:93774:27"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> the <hi>Non-conformity</hi> was <hi>conceived</hi> in the Days of King <hi>Edward,</hi> which was born in the days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a tall stripling in the days of King <hi>James,</hi> and towards the end of King <hi>Charles</hi> grown up to the <hi>full stature</hi> of a Man.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> the Reverend <hi>Hooper,</hi> scrupling certain points of <hi>Conformity,</hi> the King under his Royal Signet in the fourth year of his Reign, countenanced the <hi>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting pass certain Rites and Ceremonies offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive to his Conscience.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> in the year one thousand five hundred sixty four, began the name of <hi>Puritans,</hi> for such as <hi>dissented</hi> from the unscriptural <hi>Discipline</hi> of the Church: and by the year one thousand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred seventy two, <hi>Presbyteries</hi> begun to be erected; first at <hi>Wandsworth,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards at <hi>London.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That,</hi> in the year one thousand five hundred and eighty, threescore Ministers of the <hi>Presbyterian party,</hi> met at <hi>Cockfield</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> for a Conference about the <hi>Common-Prayer Book;</hi> and by the year one thousand five hundred eighty two, their <hi>platform of Church-Discipline</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:93774:28"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> they petitioned the Lords of the Privy-Council, confessing their zeal for the <hi>necessary Reformation of many things in the Church, according to the word of God:</hi> who thereupon solicited the <hi>Archbishop</hi> for favor to them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> in the year one thousand five hundred eighty five, the Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to correct <hi>Ecclesiastical Abuses;</hi> but the Queen being <hi>semper eadem,</hi> would let nothing of moment be alter'd in the <hi>Church-Discipline.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> in the year one thousand five hundred eighty seven, the House of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> presented unto the House of <hi>Lords</hi> a Petition, That (among other Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) Ministers might not be troubled for the Omission of some <hi>Rites</hi> prescribed in the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer.</hi> And the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> wondered, that her Majesty would in this matter make choice to confer with those who were all <hi>enemies to Reformation,</hi> because it touched their <hi>Freeholds.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> in the year one thousand five hundred eighty eight, a <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Coventry,</hi> decreed against <hi>private Baptism,</hi> against the sign of the <hi>Cross</hi> in Baptism, against the calling of <hi>Bishops,</hi> and the lawfulness of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93774:28"/> their Courts, and for teaching the <hi>Resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation of Discipline,</hi> as occasion shall serve.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> in the year one thousand five hundred eighty nine, famous Mr. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> had thirty one Articles (of <hi>Non-Conformity</hi>) before her Majesties Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, objected against him; and he, with his Brethren were sent unto the <hi>Fleet,</hi> where he secretly and silently took up his Lodging.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">That <hi>King</hi> James <hi>wrote from</hi> Scotland <hi>unto the Queen, to stay the</hi> hard usage of the Ministers of the Evangel for their diversity from the Bishops.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> after this, one Mr. <hi>Stone,</hi> who yet continued a stiff <hi>Nonconformist,</hi> made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Persecutors a <hi>discovery</hi> of the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings held by the Presbyterian Ministers at <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> at <hi>Northampton,</hi> and at <hi>Kettering.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">That <hi>Mr.</hi> Perkins, <hi>whom</hi> all Men held for a Prophet, <hi>was concurring to</hi> this Cause.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> Mr. <hi>Ʋdal,</hi> who, as <hi>Musculus</hi> first brought in the manner of preaching with <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Ʋses,</hi> was the first that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93774:29"/>
                  <hi>Reasons</hi> thereunto; a learned Man, blameless for his Life, powerful in his praying, and no less profitable than pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in his preaching, was condemned to die, for being the Author of a Book, Intituled, <hi>A Demonstration of the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which Christ hath prescribed in his Word.</hi> And <hi>the Sword of Justice</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then drawn, was not put up again into the Sheath, before others were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> there was a Petition, signed by seven hundred and fifty Preachers, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of only twenty five Countries, afoot in the year one thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and three, desiring a <hi>Reformation of certain Ceremonies and Abuses of the Church.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                  <hi>That</hi> then followed the <hi>Conference</hi> at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> by which time the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops had so made the King their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, that (after abundance of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Passages) "the King was pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to say, If this be all your Party hath to say, I will make 'em con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themselves, or else I will har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie them out of the Land, or else do worse.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93774:29"/>
            <p>And so truly he did! The King, who had once professed unto a National Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the <hi>Kirk</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">He praised God, he was King in so sincere a Church, a Church sincerer than the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whose Service was an ill-said Mass in English,</q> did now set himself to <hi>harrie out of the Land,</hi> the People who could not conform to that <hi>Service</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> The Persecutions used upon the <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> under his and the Successors influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, proceeded so far, that Multitudes of them at length sought <hi>quiet Recesses</hi> in an <hi>American</hi> Wilderness.</p>
            <p>But that in <hi>the Mouth of at least three Witnesses,</hi> our account about the degree of <hi>Reformation, designed</hi> by some, and <hi>obstruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by others, <hi>may be established,</hi> we will to these Quotations, add the Testimony of Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> who in his printed Letters, affirms, That in his <hi>Travels</hi> he had opportunity at <hi>Zurich</hi> to read a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of the Letters that passed between <hi>Bullinger,</hi> and several of our great <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> the Originals whereof were laid up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Archives there: <q rend="margDblQuotes">By which Letters it appears, that the Bishops pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served the things then contested, rather in compliance with the <hi>Queen's Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> than out of any liking they had <hi>themselves</hi> unto them. <hi>Juel</hi> in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93774:30"/>
                  <hi>February</hi> the 8th, 1566. wishes that all the <hi>Remnants of Popery</hi> might be thrown both out of the Churches, and out of the minds of the People; and laments the <hi>Queen's Fixedness</hi> unto them, so that she would suffer <hi>no change</hi> to be made. <hi>Sands</hi> writes, <hi>Contenditur de vestibus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pisticis utendis, vel non utendis; dabit Deus his quoque finem. Horn</hi> writes, that he hoped, the <hi>Act</hi> concerning <hi>Habits</hi> would be repealed at the next Session of <hi>Parliament,</hi> if the Popish Party did not hinder it. <hi>Grindal</hi> writes, That the <hi>Queen</hi> was so prepossessed in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that she continued inflexible; and <hi>Coz</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Ely</hi> laments the aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion that they found in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> unto all the Propositions that were made for the <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Abuses.</hi>
               </q> And if the Reader will further consult <hi>the History of the Reformation,</hi> written by that learned Man, he will find, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> received some Impressions in her Father's Reign, in favour of such old Rites as he had still retained, in her own nature loving State, and some <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> (as well as in every thing else;) she thought that in her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Reign they had stript it too much of <hi>external Ornaments.</hi>
               </q> Yea he will find, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That the <hi>Visiters</hi> made report to the Queen of the obedience given to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:93774:30"/> the Laws and her Injunctions; and it was found that of nine thousand four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred beneficed Men in <hi>England,</hi> there were no more but fourteen Bishops, six Abbots, twelve Deans, twelve Arch-Deacons, fifteen Heads of Colleges, fifty Prebendaries, and eighty Rectors of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishes that had left their Benefices on the account of <hi>Religion.</hi> So compliant were the <hi>Papists</hi> generally! And indeed the <hi>Bishops</hi> after this time had the same ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of the danger into which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was brought, by the <hi>Juglings</hi> of the greatest part of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> who retain'd their affections to the <hi>old Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitions,</hi> that those in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time had: so that if Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had not lived so long as she did, till all that Generation was dead, and a <hi>new set</hi> of Men better educated and principled, were grown up and put in their rooms; and if a Prince of another Religion had succeeded before that time, they had probably turned about to the <hi>old Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitions,</hi> as nimbly as they had done before in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days.</q> But if the Confessions which the most <hi>conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sons of the Church</hi> have thus made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the various disposition of men and things in the <hi>Reformation,</hi> be not satisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; <hi>Reader,</hi> take the pains to peruse the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93774:31"/> Story, which <hi>Cambden,</hi> another of them, has given us concerning the <hi>Steps</hi> which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> took in the <hi>Reformation;</hi> how many of the <hi>Popish Rites</hi> were by slow degrees <hi>rejected,</hi> and how many were still retained through her fondness for them: a Story too long to be in this place repeated. And add thereunto the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>one,</hi> who was friend enough un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Prelacy,</hi> in his Letter to <hi>Hooker</hi> about writing his <hi>Ecclesiastical Policy;</hi>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">It may be remembred that at the first, <hi>the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est part of the Learned in the Land,</hi> were either eagerly affected, or favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably inclined to that way [of <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi>]; the Books then written, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured for the most part of the <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinary Stile,</hi> it sounded every where in the Pulpits, and in the common Phrase of Men's Speech; and the <hi>contrary Party</hi> began to <hi>fear</hi> they had taken a <hi>wrong course.</hi>
               </q> Unto such <hi>incontestible Authors</hi> do I still confine my self, being terrified by the words of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who says, <q rend="margDblQuotes">To give the true History of the original Causes and Progress of our Corruptions, will not be endured by them that still justify their own and their Predecessors Sin, and can see no fault in any, but those that they first make, and then call, <hi>their Adversaries.</hi> I have found that the most notorious matters of Fact will be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93774:31"/> denied furiously by such Men, even what hath been said and done in their presence and mine, before a multitude of Witnesses, Bishops, Doctors and divers others; yea, things said and done in Parliaments, and Armies, and publickly notified, are by such Men contradicted with rage.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="9">§. 9 From this time, <hi>Reader,</hi> Behold the <hi>Church of England</hi> miserably beschism'd into <hi>Guelph</hi> and <hi>Gibelline!</hi> After this, <hi>What will ye see</hi> in the Church of <hi>England? As it were the company of two Armies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the one <hi>side</hi> [Alas, thou wretched word, SIDE, wilt croud into all our <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story,</hi> and be a word <hi>essential</hi> to all the History of the whole World, until the third Chapter of <hi>Genesis</hi> be superseded by the three last Chapters of the <hi>Revelation!</hi>] I say on the one <hi>side,</hi> there hath been a great Body of <hi>Men,</hi> desirous to enjoy for themselves, and allow and assert for others, the Liberty of <hi>Men;</hi> and at the same time, to have the <hi>Liberty wherewith Christ hath made us free,</hi> preserved inviolable: They desire, That the <hi>Reformation of Religion</hi> should be carried on in the <hi>Steps,</hi> and by the <hi>Rules</hi> which the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, speaking from the <hi>Oracle</hi> of the <hi>Sacred Scripture,</hi> hath directed; and they believe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93774:32"/> there is a PLUS ULTRA, which the great Work <hi>begun,</hi> and <hi>but begun</hi> in the last Age, is not yet arrived unto: They desire that the <hi>Qualifications</hi> for the <hi>Pastoral Office,</hi> and for <hi>Communion</hi> in all the <hi>special Ordinances</hi> of the Church, be no other than what the Lord Jesus Christ hath in <hi>his Word</hi> requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: They desire, That the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate should be entrusted with a Power to <hi>regulate,</hi> according to the word of God, any disorder in the <hi>Church,</hi> that shall have a direct influence on the <hi>State;</hi> and they confess thus far, a <hi>National Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> only they would have it recognized as no more than an <hi>Human</hi> and a <hi>Civil</hi> Policy <hi>circa Sacra.</hi> If there must be <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops,</hi> they cannot acknowledg them to have any Title unto their <hi>Dignities,</hi> but what is <hi>Humane</hi> and <hi>Civil,</hi> conferred by the <hi>King</hi> upon them, whose alone <hi>Officers</hi> they are, <hi>circa Sacra,</hi> (nor indeed was the <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino</hi>-ship hereof ever until the Days of King <hi>James</hi> the First pretended unto; but we are sure, that even a Convocation in the days of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth declared, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That there are but two Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders only, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Priests, and that of Deacons, instituted by Jesus Christ: That the Superiorities or Preheminences of one Bishop or Priest above another are, only by an human Ordinance:)</q> They desire that Parochial or Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93774:32"/> Assemblies, may be acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as <hi>particular Churches,</hi> and permitted the <hi>Rights</hi> of <hi>Churches,</hi> who may from the <hi>Pastors</hi> of their own choosing, have all the Ordinances of the Gospel, with the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Discipline</hi> administred, and have it left unto their own choice, whether they will herein have a <hi>Liturgy</hi> or no among them: They desire, That <hi>conscientious Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters</hi> from <hi>established Rites,</hi> may not be compelled, and harassed, and ruined with <hi>Civil Penalties,</hi> for the scruples of their <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Consciences;</hi> but, that <hi>Evangelical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Conviction</hi> be the only ones im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd upon them: and finally, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, That no illegal, despotick, and <hi>arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government</hi> may be imposed upon the brave <hi>English Nation:</hi> LIBERTY and PROPERTY is their cognizance. To avoid Circumlocutions, I will take the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to put upon the <hi>Side</hi> thus describ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a name that shall carry their desired Liberty in the signification of it; I will call them ELEUTHERIANS: And if the Story of our King <hi>Lucius,</hi> the <hi>first Christian King</hi> they say in the World, were certain, we would respect the name the more, for that famous old <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> who thought that the <hi>Faith of Christ, and the Old and New Testament,</hi> without any Additions from <hi>Rome,</hi> was Law enough to govern the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93774:33"/> these our <hi>ELEƲTHERIANS,</hi> or <hi>Freemen,</hi> are to be reckon'd, not only the hundreds of thousands that have actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally shaken off the Shackles of <hi>Conformity</hi> to the <hi>Popish Remainders</hi> yet vexing of <hi>England,</hi> but those also that have lived in conformity, yet groaning, or at least <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to have the heavy <hi>Yoke</hi> taken off; yea, I am not sure that the biggest part of the <hi>Conformable</hi> themselves, will not be found of this number. Such an one (<hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> I will not quote <hi>one,</hi> but what, if I mistake not, was a <hi>conformable Son of the Church</hi>) I say, such a one was Doctor <hi>Jewell,</hi> when he wrote, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for Conscience sake is a very Unchristian or Antichristian Symptom.</q> Such was Mr. <hi>Deering,</hi> when he wrote, <q rend="margDblQuotes">The Similitude which the Common-Prayer-Book hath with the form of Prayer which the Papists used, I think declineth from the equity of the Laws in the seventh and twelfth Chapters of <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> which thing our Fathers so much regarded in the Primitive Church, that their Books are full of great Complaints, against all Similitude to be had with Gentiles; and great Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency hath followed this Book, while it hath maintained an unlearned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry.</q> Such was Dr. <hi>Pilkington,</hi> when he wrote, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That he misliked our being
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93774:33"/> so like the Papists in our Liturgy; and that it is our fault generally that we differ not from them in all our Ministry.</q> Such was Dr. <hi>Bilson,</hi> when he wrote, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That the Reformed Churches are so far from admitting the full dose of the Heresies of the Papists, that by no means they can digest a dram of their Ceremonies.</q> Such was Dr. <hi>Humphry,</hi> when he wrote, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That we ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to conform our selves unto the Enemies of God in any of their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; and that he wish'd and hop'd for the utter abolishing of all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of Popish Superstition, which yet remain in our Church.</q> Such was Dr. <hi>Fulk,</hi> when he wrote, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That if a Man mislike our Form of Divine Service, as not sufficiently differing from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, he shows his greatest zeal in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of their Idolatry and Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: We abhor whatsoever hath but a shew of Popery.</q> Such was Dr. <hi>More,</hi> when he wrote, <q rend="margDblQuotes">It is an Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Use of Church-Government, to direct it to the upholding of scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Ceremonies, and ensnaring Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men; and what is it but Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and barbarous Cruelty, to afflict Men for what they cannot help, and in what they do not sin? And what but plain Rebellion against God, to wrest
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93774:34"/> his Scepter out of his hand, by which he ruleth in the Consciences of Men, and to usurp this Empire to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves! A mutual agreement in bearing with one another's Dissents in the Non-fundamentals of Religion, is really a greater Ornament, than the most exact Uniformity imaginable; it being an eminent exercise of Charity, the Flower of all Christian Graces, and the best way I think at the long-run, to make the Church as uniform as can justly be desired.</q> To have done: Such was Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> whose emphatical Words are these; <q rend="margDblQuotes">Require of Christians only to believe Christ, and to call no Man Master but him only; let those leave claiming of Infallibility, who have no right unto it, and let them that in their words disclaim it, disclaim it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in their Actions: In a word, take away Tyranny, which is the Devil's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument to support Errors, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitions, and Impieties in the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of the World, which could not otherwise long withstand the Power of Truth; I say, take away Tyranny, and restore Christians to their just and full liberty of captivating their Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to the Scripture only; that universal Liberty thus moderated, may quickly reduce <hi>Christendom</hi> to Truth and Unity.</q>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:93774:34"/> And what but such were those <hi>Episcopal Divines,</hi> who with Dr. <hi>Ʋsher</hi> presented unto the Parliament above thirty <hi>Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> against the <hi>Liturgy?</hi> I will descend no lower, I will produce no more; here is enough to explain one side of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Controversies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other side; there hath been a prevailing Party, whose Grief it hath been, that ever the <hi>Reformation</hi> proceeded so far, and whose Wrath hath been on all occasions vented against the Memory of those that were chief in the <hi>Reformation. Reader,</hi> call them not that <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which is the <hi>Spouse of Christ;</hi> but let the name of LOT's WIFE be assign'd unto them, and let them upon good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <hi>remember her.</hi> These IDUMAEANS would monopolize unto themselves the name of <hi>the Church of England;</hi> but they have by <hi>Canons</hi> boldly invading of, and contrary to the <hi>Parliamentary Power,</hi> form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>new Church of England,</hi> which for more than half an hundred years after the <hi>Reformation,</hi> t'would have been little short of <hi>Treason</hi> to have talk'd of. They have made their <hi>Church-Government,</hi> by <hi>Arch-Bishops, Bishops, Deans, Arch-Deacons,</hi> and the rest that bear Office in the Church, a thing of <hi>Divine Right;</hi> but then they durst not show their Head: for, from the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:93774:35"/> King they now derive not their <hi>Episcopal Authority,</hi> as they did at the beginning: Their Eye is upon a <hi>foreign Jurisdiction!</hi> They have made no more than <hi>twenty six particular Churches,</hi> namely the <hi>Diocesan,</hi> in the whole <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and with a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Impudence they dare to publish it, <hi>Inauditus erat parochorum pastoratus ante hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus seculi, &amp; antecedentis Delirium;</hi> and blotting out the name of <hi>Pastor,</hi> where their Books formerly so called the <hi>Parish-Presbyter,</hi> they have left unto none, but the <hi>twenty six Bishops,</hi> either <hi>Obligation</hi> to <hi>teach,</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> to rule in the Church. They have been meer <hi>Bigots</hi> for trifling <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;</hi> and if they could but <hi>cozen</hi> Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Belief, that it was a brave piece of <hi>devotion,</hi> to have a <hi>Church</hi> set off (like that of <hi>Durham,</hi> described by Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi>) with an <hi>Altar</hi> and <hi>Cherubims,</hi> which cost two thousand Pounds, and an <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Anthems</hi> of the three Kings of <hi>Collen,</hi> to be sung instead of <hi>Psalms,</hi> before and after Sermon, and a conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated <hi>Knife</hi> to cut the <hi>Bread</hi> at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and abundance more of such <hi>Trinkets,</hi> they have seemed as if they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, tho the <hi>Substantials</hi> of the <hi>Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Religion</hi> were utterly lost in the Nation. All the Doctrines of <hi>Grace,</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted by the true Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:93774:35"/> these men do first <hi>Subscribe</hi> them, and then <hi>Preach</hi> and <hi>Print</hi> against them, and with these, if a man would be <hi>preferred,</hi> he must be a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian.</hi> Lest <hi>Christianity</hi> should be consistent with <hi>Conformity,</hi> these men also are they that once invented a <hi>Proclamation for Sports on the Lord's Day,</hi> as an Engine to vex the best <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> among the <hi>Conformists,</hi> and fill the Land with <hi>Paganism</hi> and <hi>Atheism:</hi> And this in spite of the <hi>Homilies</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which damn'd them for doing so. They have exacted from the <hi>Clergy,</hi> an <hi>Assent</hi> and <hi>Consent</hi> unto every thing in the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> the Book of Consecrating <hi>Bishops,</hi> and Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> and <hi>Homilies;</hi> and the <hi>Clergy</hi> are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That they will never <hi>endeavour</hi> any <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration</hi> of the Ecclesiastical Constitution; yea, to <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Swear</hi> that they will observe all the <hi>Canons.</hi> By these <hi>Canons,</hi>
               <q rend="margSglQuotes">Whosoever shall affirm, That the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by Law Established, is not a <hi>Church</hi> formed according to <hi>Divine Institution;</hi> or whosoever affirms, That its Worship contained in the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and Administration of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> is Corrupt; or that any of the <hi>Thirty Nine Articles,</hi> are in any part Superstitious or Erroneous, or such as he may not with a good Conscience <hi>Subscribe</hi> unto; or that the <hi>Rites and Ceremonies</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are such as being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Lawful Authority, men who are zealously and godlily affected, may not with a good Conscience approve them; or that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93774:36"/> the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Archbishops, Bishops,</hi> &amp;c. is Repugnant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Word of God; are to be Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, <hi>Ipso facto,</hi> and not to be restored until they repent, and publickly revoke such their <hi>wicked Errors.</hi> By these <hi>Canons,</hi> 'All such are <hi>Accursed,</hi> who combine themselves in a <hi>New Brotherhood,</hi> or affirm that such Ministers as refuse to <hi>Subscribe</hi> unto the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion-Book,</hi> and their <hi>Adherents,</hi> may truly take unto themselves the Names of <hi>another Church,</hi> not Established by Law, and dare presume to publish it; that this <hi>pretended Church</hi> hath of long time groaned under the burthen of some certain <hi>Grievances</hi> imposed upon the Members thereof: Or, whosoever shall maintain, That there are within the Realm other Meetings, Assemblies, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, of the Kings Born Subjects, than such as by the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land are allowed, which may rightly challenge to themselves the name of True and Lawful <hi>Churches.</hi> By these <hi>Canons,</hi> none may have their Children <hi>Baptized,</hi> who dare not sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto the <hi>Cross</hi> and <hi>Godfathers;</hi> and all those that refuse to <hi>Kneel</hi> at the Reception of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and to be present at <hi>publick Prayers;</hi> or who refuse Reverently to <hi>Kneel,</hi> when the General <hi>Confession, Litany,</hi> and other <hi>Prayers</hi> are Read, and will not <hi>stand</hi> up, at the Saying of the <hi>Belief,</hi> and <hi>Bow</hi> at the Name of <hi>Jesus,</hi> nor <hi>say</hi> in their due place, and audibly, with the Minister the <hi>Confession,</hi> the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Creed,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:93774:36"/> nor make such other <hi>Answers</hi> to the <hi>Publick Prayers</hi> as are appointed, all such are to be denied the <hi>Communion;</hi> and what Minister soever shall wittingly admit them, he is lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a <hi>Suspension.</hi>
               </q> With these men (to quote still none but <hi>Conformable Authors</hi> for every thing, Reader, now 'tis one <hi>Hickringale,</hi> and no <hi>Nonconformist,</hi> that is my Voucher) <hi>A pretended hatred against Popery, is nothing but a Colour wherewith Hypocrisy hath still painted the ugly face of hatred and malice against the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious.</hi> While these men can assert the <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Heathens,</hi> they cannot allow an <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> to <hi>Christians:</hi> And though they Blaspheme it as a <hi>Tyranny</hi> for the Almighty to <hi>Punish men for what they can't help,</hi> they themselves very <hi>Tyrannically</hi> practise it. These Men, being by <hi>Divine Providence</hi> made capable for the most part very much to influence the <hi>Legislative Power,</hi> have procured those <hi>Laws</hi> to be Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against <hi>Conscientious Dissenters,</hi> a mere <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract</hi> whereof, were enough to fill many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, well deserving the Title of <hi>Draconica; Laws,</hi> which gave the Earl of <hi>Castlemain,</hi> a <hi>Papist,</hi> cause to say in Print, <q rend="margSglQuotes">It was never known that <hi>Rome</hi> Persecuted (as the <hi>Bishops</hi> do) those who adhere to the <hi>same Faith</hi> with themselves, and Established an <hi>Inquisition</hi> against the Professors of the <hi>strictest Piety</hi> among themselves: And however the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates complain of the Bloody Persecution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> it is manifest <hi>their</hi> Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution exceeds it; for under <hi>her</hi> there were not more than <hi>Two or Three hundred</hi> put to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:93774:37"/> Death; whereas under <hi>their</hi> Persecution, there hath above treble that Number been stifled, destroyed, and ruined in their Estates, Lives, and Liberties, being (as is most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable) men for the most part of the <hi>same Spirit and Principle</hi> with those Protestants who suffered under the <hi>Prelates</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s time.</q> In the Execution of those <hi>Laws,</hi> wherein
<q xml:lang="lat">Dat veniam Corvis, vexat censura Columbas.</q> What three Volumes of <hi>Martyrology</hi> in <hi>Folio</hi> could enumerate the unaccountable <hi>Oppressions</hi> used upon the <hi>best Christians</hi> in the Nation? While at the same time the most <hi>Ungodly</hi> Wretches of all sorts, and the scoffers and haters of all <hi>Godliness,</hi> have been encouraged as the truest <hi>Sons of the Church:</hi> Persons of <hi>Caesar Borgia</hi>'s Qualifications can live in the <hi>Communion of the Church,</hi> with these men, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all manner of encouragement; while the most <hi>serious Piety, exemplified</hi> in <hi>all manner of Conversation,</hi> could not secure those that scrupled any of their pitiful <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> from as cruel Censures as ever the <hi>Wolf</hi> and the <hi>Fox,</hi> which in the <hi>ancient Apologue,</hi> Absolved one another from the guilt of their confessed Villanies, pass'd upon the poor <hi>Ass</hi> for touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Pilgrims <hi>pad of Straw.</hi> Nor could <hi>Conformity</hi> neither, secure the <hi>seriously Religious</hi> from the rage of that Spirit whereby these men have been acted; but as it is expressed and complained by Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> a <hi>Conformable</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:93774:37"/> Divine, (for indeed, Reader, in these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I durst not quote a <hi>Nonconformist) with such as these, if any man press for Regeneration, Sanctification, and an holy life, he was to pass heretofore for a</hi> Puritan, <hi>then for a</hi> Round-head, <hi>now for a damn'd</hi> Fanatick; <hi>nor shall he escape this censure, though he be never so great a</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>and do exactly conform to the Church, as now by Law Established; for 'tis</hi> Holiness <hi>they hate more than Noncoformity.</hi> Yea, no less Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons than the <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> have been put upon, signifying with grief under their hands, unto an <hi>Archbishop, That a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ministers (conformable enough) zealous and learned Preachers; have been Deprived and Suspended, and their Places left without any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry or Preaching, Prayers and Sacraments; or certain Persons appointed unto those void Rooms, who were Persons neither of Learning nor of good Names; yea, a great number notoriously unfit, chargeable with Ignorance, and with great enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Faults, as Drunkenness, Filthiness of life, Gaming at Cards, haunting of Ale-houses, and such like; against whom we hear not of any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, but that they are quietly suffered, to the slander of the Church, to the offence of good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; yea, to the Famishing of them for want of good Teaching.</hi> This is that <hi>Faction</hi> who pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish unto Mankind their <hi>Spirit</hi> in such Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as this, <hi>That they abhor being a</hi> Papist <hi>as much as being a</hi> Presbyterian, <hi>and that they will as soon be</hi> Turks <hi>as be either of them.</hi> What shall I say more? In the <hi>Church</hi> they have broken down the <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Churches</hi> which our
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:93774:38"/> Lord Jesus Christ Instituted; they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed his <hi>Officers;</hi> they have destroyed his <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> they have laid aside his <hi>Rules</hi> of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they have set up <hi>New things</hi> of their <hi>own</hi> quite opposite unto <hi>His:</hi> Yet they lay claim to all the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of <hi>His;</hi> and all this they do in <hi>his name;</hi> which is an Iniquity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily <hi>aggravated,</hi> extraordinarily <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated!</hi> In the <hi>State</hi> what they have done shall not be reported in any words of mine; but, <hi>Ex ore tuo, Serve Nequam.</hi> They have taught, with <hi>Manwayring, That the King, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out common Consent in Parliament, could by his Command so far bind the Subject to say Taxes, that they cannot refuse the Payment of them without Peril of eternal Damnation; and that the Authority of Parliament was not necessary to the raising of Subsidies.</hi> They have Taught, with <hi>Heylin, Princes are God's Deputies; Of whom should they be limited? If you say by the Laws of the Land; those themselves have made,</hi> Principi Lex non est posita; <hi>They are above the Law and have an Absolute Authority.</hi> They have Taught with <hi>Lesley, That Princes being God's Legislators, are above their Laws, and Dispense with them as they think expedient.</hi> They have Taught with <hi>Wemius, In Monarchiâ, Regis sola voluntas, de substantiâ Legis est; praevia populi Consultatio, non est Necessaria.</hi> They have Taught, as a later <hi>Meteor</hi> in the <hi>English</hi> Heavens hath Illuminated us; <hi>That as well Inferior Magistrates, as others, employed by a Popish or Tyrannical Prince, in the most illegal and outragious acts of Violence, such as Cutting of Throats, and the like, are Irresistible,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:93774:38"/> and must be submitted to under pain of eternal Damnation.</hi> Yea, that the Note may be carried <hi>high</hi> enough unto all their fulsome Idolatry of their <hi>Charles the First,</hi> they have added the Blasphemy of calling him <hi>CHRIST the Second:</hi> And one <hi>Parker</hi> in a Treatise of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> published 1684, thus expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed himself; <hi>It is but a Crude expression, not to call it Profane (because it is so common by custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary mistake) to affirm that Kings are Supream Governors under Christ: They are and ever were so, under God, but so as to be Superior to Christ, as Christ is Head of the Church within their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> I am already weary of Transcribing their <hi>Tantivee</hi> stuff, and will conclude it with the words of one that is a <hi>Conformable</hi> Son of the Church, [for still I durst not quote a <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formist</hi>] who says, <hi>Non-Resistence and Passive Obedience, were the only Orthodox and Catholick Doctrines, so long as they imagined it would never come unto their own turn to practise them. When the men of this stamp had once gained the Prince on their side, and to espouse their Interest, they have endeavoured to requite him by ascribing to him an Absolute Power, and Illimited Authority over the Subject; though none winc'd sooner, nor kick'd higher at it, when they themselves began to feel the dint of it.</hi> I shall proceed no farther in <hi>Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizing</hi> this <hi>Carcase</hi> of a <hi>Church:</hi> Pope <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> VIII. threatned a Thunderbolt of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> against every <hi>Physician</hi> that should venture to do the part of an <hi>Anatomist;</hi> and I have already employed my Knife so far in my <hi>Dissections,</hi> that certain <hi>Canons</hi> made by as
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93774:39"/> good Authority as <hi>Boniface</hi>'s, have <hi>ipso facto</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated me.</p>
            <p>I called them <hi>IDUMAEANS;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause whether we consider their <hi>contempt</hi> of what every Right <hi>Christian,</hi> and every Right <hi>Englishman</hi> values as his <hi>Birth-right;</hi> or consider the <hi>Bloody Rage</hi> with which they came out against their <hi>Brethren,</hi> who in some sort have been <hi>Twins</hi> with them, they will appear to us the true Sons of <hi>Edom;</hi> and because they may read more than they are aware of their <hi>own Fate,</hi> if they will please to consult the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies in the ancient Oracles of Heaven about the <hi>Edomites;</hi> to the sense of which <hi>Prophecies,</hi> I remember there is a notable <hi>Key</hi> given us by the <hi>Jewish Rabbies,</hi> על רגמי אמרו, <hi>Of</hi> ROME <hi>have they spoken it.</hi> But they like not their <hi>Scripture Name,</hi> let them still keep their old Right <hi>English Name</hi> of UNRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORMABLES.</p>
            <p n="10">§. 10. No less a man than Sir <hi>Francis Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singham,</hi> in his account of the Severities used by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> against the <hi>Puritans,</hi> (a Nick-name devised first by <hi>Sanders</hi> the Jesuite, for the <hi>best</hi> men in the Kingdom, and by the <hi>worst</hi> ever after put upon them) confesses, <hi>That when they resolved</hi> (at last) <hi>to carry on their designs, without waiting for the consent of the Magistrate, upon that the Queen found it neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to restrain them.</hi> And <hi>Cambden</hi> [one far from a <hi>Nonconformist</hi>] is our Author for it, <hi>That Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>advancing</hi> Whitgift <hi>unto the See of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>above all commanded him
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93774:39"/> to re-establish the Discipline of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>that as then lay dismembred by the conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency of Prelates, the obstinacy of Innovators, and the power of some great ones; whilst some Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters utterly condemned the Liturgy, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed manner of Administring the Sacraments, as being in many things contrary to the Scripture.</hi> Nor is it unknown that the proceedings of <hi>Whitgift</hi> hereupon, were such as to procure him from the Lord Treasurer <hi>Burleigh</hi> a Letter dated, <hi>July</hi> 5. 1584. wherein he tells him, <hi>I think the Inquisitors of</hi> Spain <hi>use not so many Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions to trap their Preys: This kind of Proceeding is too much savouring the</hi> Romish <hi>Inquisition.</hi> The terrible <hi>Persecution</hi> which afterwards followed upon the <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> would be too long and sad a Story to be in this place largely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated: <hi>Afflicti Suppliciis</hi> Puritani, <hi>Genus Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> [Forsooth!] <hi>Superstitionis Novae &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leficae!</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> in a Book Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1647. Writes, That there was then in <hi>New-England</hi> a Fourth Volume of the Books of <hi>Martyrs</hi> in <hi>Manuscript</hi> beginning, where Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> left off, and containing the Sufferings of Godly men (and Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> himself, perhaps one of them) from the Enemies of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> for their expressing their desires to have it further car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on. But Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> being a <hi>Nonconformist,</hi> I must fly presently to a more <hi>Conformable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor;</hi> it shall be old Bishop <hi>Morton,</hi> who ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly urged the <hi>Puritans</hi> to be as <hi>Conformable</hi> as himself, with such wonderful words as these; <hi>I ought not to esteem any thing a just cause of Silencing my self from Preaching, for which I
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:93774:40"/> ought not as willingly to venture my life. The Nonconformist have suffered what is next to Death, and too many have suffered even unto Death in Prisons, where several caught their Death, and others Died; Of whom shall their Deaths be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red?</hi> And I suppose the <hi>Puritans</hi> then knew how to retort upon this Reverend Bishop, his own words; <hi>Not of our own selves, Doctor!</hi> (might they have said) <hi>but of you, that would venture to Silence good men, and even to take away their lives, for things for which you thought they should not venture their lives.</hi> All Mankind then saw no less than <hi>Three hundred Ministers</hi> (whom the most Learned <hi>Parker</hi> compares to the <hi>Three hundred Soldiers of</hi> Gideon) all of them in <hi>one</hi> particular storm Deprived of their Ministry and their Maintenance, because they could not <hi>Subscribe</hi> to some <hi>unlawful Impositions.</hi> No less a man than Sir <hi>Edward Dearing,</hi> in the most August Assembly under Heaven, could then complain, <hi>With the Papists there is a severe Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, and with us a bitter High Commission.</hi> Yea, the Book Entituled, <hi>The Register of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Matters touching the Reformation,</hi> records a Story about a Congregation of an Hundred Persons who refused the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and had the <hi>purer Ordinances</hi> of the Gospel among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, in the Year 1567. for which they Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered not a little. And after what fashion some of these Confessors were handled in those days, the Reader shall understand, <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ab uno,</hi> which I find (reported by a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formist</hi>) thus; <q rend="margSglQuotes">Mr. <hi>John Heyden,</hi> a <hi>Devonshire</hi> Minister, in a Sermon preach'd at <hi>Norwich,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:93774:40"/> let fall some passages against setting up of <hi>Images,</hi> and Bowing at the Name of <hi>Jesus;</hi> he was hereon Apprehended like a Traytor, with the Constables Bills and Halberts, and brought before Dr. <hi>Harsnett,</hi> then Bishop, and Manacled like a Felon, and Committed by him close Prisoner to the Common Goal, above Thirteen Weeks, where he was like to <hi>Starve</hi> (the Bishop having taken from him his Horse, Papers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) from whence he was by a Pursevant convey'd to <hi>London,</hi> and kept Two full Terms; at last, by the <hi>High Commission,</hi> he was Deprived of his <hi>Orders;</hi> thereafter the <hi>High Commissioners</hi> Imprisoned him in the <hi>Gate-house common Dungeon,</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> sent him to be Whipt in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Bridewell,</hi> and then kept him all the long extreme Cold Winter in a dark cold Dungeon, without Fire or Candle, Chain'd to a Post in the midst of the Room, with heavy Irons on his Hands and Feet, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him only Bread and Water, with a Pad of Straw to lie upon; and on his Release, caused him to take an <hi>Oath</hi> and give <hi>Bond</hi> to Preach no more, and to depart the Kingdom in Three Weeks without returning.</q> Reader, 'tis a kind of <hi>Inhumanity</hi> to relate such horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things; what hath been related is enough to make way for the passage that must now follow thereupon. To undergo much Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Misery, with daily fears of Massacre from <hi>Indian</hi> Salvages, in a bleak Region, a Thousand Leagues from ones own Country, is a sad condition; but if the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93774:41"/>
               <hi>Gospel</hi> may be had with it, the condition was by some Thousands of Good men judged not so sad and so hard, as that of being in the <hi>Griping Talons</hi> of Archbishop <hi>LAUD.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Mankind will not now wonder at it, That a Number of <hi>Nonconformists</hi> chose to <hi>fly into a Wilderness,</hi> where they might Peaceably erect <hi>Evangelical Churches,</hi> and pursue the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs</hi> of a <hi>Scriptural Reformation,</hi> and enjoy the Spiritual <hi>Blessings</hi> of a <hi>Reformed State,</hi> rather than both feel and give the <hi>Disturbance</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Differences</hi> here at home exposed them. An <hi>American Wilderness,</hi> now known by the Name of <hi>NEW-ENGLAND,</hi> was on this occasion, between the Years 1620 and 1640, Peopled with <hi>Evangelical Churches,</hi> by such as were driven out of the Realm of <hi>England</hi> through the <hi>Persecutions</hi> of <hi>Ceremony-Mongers,</hi> that ever were, and ever will be <hi>Enemies</hi> to all the true <hi>Interests of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">§. 11. 'Tis true, That the Party in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which <hi>hates to be Reformed,</hi> hath, for the most part, through I know not what Advantages, hitherto been <hi>Uppermost.</hi> And hence not only the <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> which was only commenced in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Age, hath ever since been stopt, but also the <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> in the very <hi>Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Points</hi> of the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> then compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, has been in danger to be utterly lost. When the Church first Rose from the Grave of the <hi>Antichristian Apostacy,</hi> wherein she had so long been <hi>Buried,</hi> she had, like <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:93774:41"/> her <hi>Grave Cloaths</hi> hanging about her; but this Party have with a <hi>success</hi> equal to their <hi>fervour,</hi> and a <hi>fervour</hi> equal to their <hi>folly,</hi> endeavoured still to keep upon her those <hi>Monuments</hi> of her former <hi>Misery.</hi> For <hi>Discipline,</hi> they have still been in the humour of those <hi>Islanders,</hi> who held it an Impiety to sweep a Room after it had contracted the Dust of Three Generations; and when the <hi>Word of Christ</hi> hath been urged with never so much of Irresistible, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contestable Evidence by them who thirsted after a <hi>better Order;</hi> there hath still been little better Answer given, than what the Prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the <hi>Convocation</hi> Silenced <hi>Philpot</hi> withal, <hi>You have the Word, and we have the Sword.</hi> But an old Observation, in the <hi>Homilies</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> hath been too much veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the <hi>Practies</hi> of them that would be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led so, <hi>That such hath been the corrupt Inclination of man, Superstitiously given to make new Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God of his own Head, and then to have more Affection and Devotion to keep that, than to search out God's Holy Commandments and to do them.</hi> For <hi>Doctrine,</hi> 'tis well known that Hundreds of thousands of <hi>Romanists</hi> at this day, distinguished by the Name of <hi>Jansenists,</hi> are Sounder in many Essential and Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Points of the <hi>Christian Faith,</hi> than many that have Subscribed our most Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox <hi>Articles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and then pretend them to be <hi>Articles</hi> not of <hi>Faith,</hi> but of <hi>Peace:</hi> Or else the famous Letter to the Rector of <hi>Brussels</hi> had never bragg'd, <hi>Now we have planted that Sovereign Drug,</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianism,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93774:42"/>
               <hi>which we hope will purge the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants from their Heresy; and it flourisheth and bears fruit in due Season.</hi> The Learned <hi>Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aldus,</hi> I remember, speaks of a <hi>Florentine</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician, whom all the Friends he had could not persuade so much as once to view the Heavens through a <hi>Telescope,</hi> and the <hi>unreasonable man</hi> gave this <hi>reason</hi> for his refusal, Because he was afraid that then his <hi>Eyes</hi> would from <hi>Ocular Demonstrations,</hi> make him stagger concerning the truth of <hi>Aristotle</hi>'s Principles, which he was resolved he would never call in Question. Our <hi>Unreformable</hi> Churchmen seem to have been as much afraid of bringing <hi>Ecclesiastical Matters</hi> under a fair Examination by the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of Truth,</hi> lest they should plainly <hi>see</hi> with their <hi>Eyes,</hi> a necessity of Proceeding to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther measures of <hi>Reformation.</hi> When an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Parliament</hi> was but bringing in a Bill against <hi>Pluralities,</hi> that <hi>eternal Scandal of Christianity,</hi> the <hi>Archbishop Whitgift,</hi> writes to the Queen with as much distress as if they were all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be <hi>Martyr'd</hi> at the Stake; <hi>The woful and distressed Estate</hi> (saith he) <hi>whereinto we are likely to fall, forceth us, with grief of Heart, in most humble manner, to crave Your Majesty's most Sovereign Protection: We beseech Your Highness's favourable beholding of our present State, and what it will be in time, if the Bill against Pluralities should take place.</hi> And when the Parliament was bringing in a <hi>Bill</hi> against another of the Abuses then Oppressing of Mankind, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains to the Queen with hideous Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, That it <hi>would tend to the Dishonour of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:93774:42"/> Church, as having hitherto maintained an Error. Then</hi> 'twas that the great <hi>Zanchy</hi> (in the Year 1571.) Addressed Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for an Abatement of the unhappy <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> concluding, <hi>It is to be feared that the Fire is so kindled, and casteth its flames so far and wide, that all the Churches of Your most mighty King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to the most perpetual Disgrace of Your most Renowned Majesty, will be set on flaming fire.</hi> But the sense of the Reformed Churches beyond Sea, thus expressed by the <hi>great Light of Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberg,</hi> would not be regarded until indeed all came to be <hi>set on a flame of Fire. Then</hi> 'twas that the Reverend <hi>John Fox</hi> entred into his <hi>Martyrology,</hi> his complaints about those <hi>Baits of Popery,</hi> and his wishes, <hi>God take them away, or ease us from them, for God knows they be the cause of much Blindness and Strife amongst men.</hi> But the unhappy causes of <hi>Blindness</hi> and <hi>Strife</hi> have still continued, until they have produced matter enough to fill another <hi>Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rology.</hi> After what fashion the Church hath since those times jogg'd on with the old <hi>Mumpsimus's,</hi> I had rather the Pen of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formist</hi> than mine should relate; and let such a Pen ['tis the Witty <hi>Marvel</hi>'s] now observe it unto us; <q rend="margSglQuotes">There are a <hi>particular Bran</hi> of Persons, who, in spite of Fate, will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, <hi>The Church of</hi> England, and to shew they are <hi>Pluralists,</hi> never do write in a modester Style, than <hi>We, We;</hi> nay, even these, several of them, are men of Parts, sufficient to deserve a Rank among the Teachers and Governors of the Church.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93774:43"/> Only what Bishop <hi>Bramhall</hi> saith of <hi>Grotius</hi> his defect in School Divinity, <hi>Unum hoc Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceror, &amp; doleo tibi deesse;</hi> I may apply to this excess and rigour in matter of <hi>Discipline;</hi> they want all consideration, all Moderation in those things; and I never heard of any of them at any time, who if they got into Power or Office, did ever make the least Experiment or Overture towards the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church and Nation they lived in. They are men of a <hi>Fiery Nature,</hi> that must always be <hi>uppermost,</hi> and so they increase their own <hi>Splendor,</hi> care not though they set all on a <hi>flame</hi> about them. You would think the same day that they took up <hi>Divinity,</hi> they divested themselves of <hi>Humanity;</hi> and so they may procure and execute a <hi>Law</hi> against the <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> that they had forgot the <hi>Gospel.</hi> They cannot endure that <hi>Humility,</hi> that <hi>Meekness,</hi> that <hi>Strictness</hi> of Manners and Conversation, which is the true way of gaining <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to the <hi>Clergy;</hi> much less can they content themselves with the ordinary and comfortable Provision that is made for the <hi>Ministry,</hi> but having wholly calculated themselves for <hi>Preferment</hi> and <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur,</hi> they know and practise no other means to make themselves venerable, but by <hi>Ceremony</hi> and <hi>Severity.</hi>
               </q> Upon the <hi>Restoration</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, there was a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular opportunity for the <hi>Reformation</hi> to have gain'd, at least, as much Establishment as was promised in that King's <hi>Declaration about Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Affairs;</hi> a <hi>Declaration</hi> whereof a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:93774:43"/> Divine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> could say, <hi>If ever a Divine Sentence was in the mouth of a King, it was with His Majesty, in that admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Declaration; and the united Judgment of the whole Nation, cannot frame a more unexceptiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expedient for a firm Concord of these distracted Churches.</hi> But this <hi>Declaration</hi> was immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of as little regard, as the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant.</hi> Though there were then a <hi>Conference</hi> about those Affairs, between the <hi>Episcopal</hi> and the <hi>Nonconformist</hi> Divines, by the <hi>King's Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> such was the event, that I still choose to give the Story in the very words of a <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist;</hi>
               <q rend="margSglQuotes">I admire (says my Author) that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such an Occasion they could not in any <hi>one thing</hi> be gratified; not so much as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing the Lessons of the <hi>Apocrypha;</hi> inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that, as many remember well, after a long tug at the <hi>Convocation-House</hi> about that matter, a good Doctor came out at last with great Exultation, <hi>That they had carried it for Bell and the Dragon.</hi>
               </q> And that the Story may be yet a little more perfect, the words of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Conformist</hi> shall be adjoined; <q rend="margSglQuotes">Many to this day think (says my Author) that the <hi>Leaves</hi> of that <hi>Plant</hi> might have conduced much to the <hi>Healing of the Nation;</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead thereof a <hi>Corrosive</hi> was provided, which Invenom'd, but never Healed the <hi>Hurt of the Daughter of our People.</hi> His Majesty soon after this <hi>Interim</hi> (which was but like <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> before a <hi>Thunderbolt</hi>) Enacted a <hi>Law,</hi> which Deprived above <hi>Twenty hundred</hi> of the Dissenting Clergy, leaving them to the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:93774:44"/> Charity of their Friends to provide Bread for themselves, and Ruined Families. By this <hi>Act</hi> was required a Subscription to the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and to give an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Assent and Consent</hi> unto all and every thing contained in it, (which was Revised and Reprinted with divers <hi>Alterations</hi>) and to be done by <hi>such a day</hi> upon pain of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation;</hi> which time was so limited, that the <hi>New Copies</hi> could not be distributed, nor what was to be Subscribed, consulted: Which hath often caused some to think, that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons then <hi>Ejected</hi> by that <hi>Law,</hi> were not <hi>Legally Ejected;</hi> for the <hi>Ignorance</hi> in that case was <hi>invincible,</hi> the Copies not being to be procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in time. How can a man be <hi>disseized</hi> of his <hi>Free-hold</hi> for not doing a thing which is <hi>Impossible</hi> and <hi>Impracticable?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then</hi> it was that the <hi>Parliament,</hi> since known by the Name of <hi>Pensioner,</hi> were so <hi>Priest-ridden</hi> as to Enact those horrid Laws for <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> by which the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of the Nation was torn to pieces; Millions of <hi>Perjuries</hi> fill'd the Land; the most <hi>bruitish</hi> of <hi>men</hi> were hired to do the most <hi>bruitish</hi> of <hi>things; Convictions</hi> were made, and <hi>Penalties</hi> were laid, not only without <hi>Juries,</hi> but also without any hearing of the Accused; <hi>Estates</hi> were Seized and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezzel'd; <hi>Houses</hi> were broke up and disturbed; <hi>Families</hi> were scattered and ruined; the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> were fill'd with the most <hi>serious Christians;</hi> and <hi>Reverend Ministers</hi> of the Gospel sent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Stocks</hi> and the <hi>Houses of Correction</hi> all over the Kingdom, for nothing but because
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:93774:44"/> their <hi>Consciences</hi> could not <hi>Conform</hi> to sinful <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies,</hi> which in the Judgment of the <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers</hi> were but <hi>Indifferent.</hi> Thus <hi>Edom did pursue his Brother with the Sword, and cast off all pity; his Anger did tear perpetually, and he kept his wrath for ever;</hi> till God <hi>sent a Fire upon them.</hi> I have read concerning <hi>Zoroaster</hi>'s Book, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled <hi>The Similitude,</hi> That it required no less than <hi>Twelve hundred and sixty Ox Hides for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of it.</hi> I know not how far the full Story of the Sufferings of the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> under the <hi>Caroline</hi> Persecution would go to fill a Book of such enormous Dimensions; this I know, 'twas a <hi>Persecution</hi> too terrible to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a <hi>Similitude;</hi> and there is a worthy Writer who does not scruple to say, That if the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of Good men in this <hi>Persecution</hi> were distinctly written, our largest <hi>Books of Martyrs</hi> would be but an <hi>Enchiridion</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of this <hi>History.</hi> At length to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd upon them for their Joining, as they <hi>always did,</hi> with the <hi>Sober part</hi> of the Nation against the <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> there fell upon them the <hi>Storm,</hi> which not only cost many of them their Lives, but also utterly dissipated their <hi>Congregations.</hi> Their Adversaries then kept a <hi>Day of Thanksgiving</hi> through the Kingdom; and in this doleful state they lay <hi>Three Years and an half;</hi> even till the <hi>Laws,</hi> which some think were made by <hi>no Authority,</hi> received ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from God or Man, came <hi>strangely</hi> (and at last fairly) to be removed. Since the most happy Accession of Their Majesties, King <hi>William</hi> and (the late) Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> to the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:93774:45"/> Throne of the Three Kingdoms, the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to Prosecute the <hi>Reformation</hi> hath been wonderfully renewed and increased, not only in the readiness which those excellent <hi>Princes</hi> have shewn in many instances to <hi>Relieve the Oppressed</hi> Consciences of the <hi>Protestant Dissenters,</hi> but also in their earnest calling upon the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the <hi>English Nation</hi> to prepare and offer <hi>Things for the good Order, Edification, and Unity of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and the Reconciling as much as is possible, all Differences among the good Subjects, and to take away all occasions of the like for the future.</hi> Nevertheless we cannot learn that any great matter hath hitherto been done by them, to answer the expectation of the <hi>Best of Princes;</hi> but excepting the <hi>Indulgence</hi> granted unto the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> by an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> all things remain so much in the old posture, as to produce this Complaint of a worthy Person, one Mr. <hi>Snowden,</hi> who is yet a <hi>Conformable Son of the Church — Ever since the Reformation</hi> (saith he) <hi>the Church hath suffered many a bitter pang for the sake of these Offensive Rites and Ceremonies: They once fretted out her Bowels, and have been, ever since their Restoration with</hi> Charles <hi>the Second, as Moths fretting her Garments: They have been the constant Troublers of our Israel; and I am afraid, if, with</hi> Jonas <hi>they be not cast overboard, they will at one time or another sink our Ship.</hi> After these mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied and emphatical Overtures, there comes forth unto the World, a <hi>Vox Cleri,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of consenting unto the <hi>Abatement</hi> of any one <hi>Apocryphal Ingredient</hi> in Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:93774:45"/> does propose the <hi>Addition</hi> of more, and the <hi>Appointment</hi> of Reading sometimes in the Church for the <hi>further Enlightening of our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,</hi> certain Portions out of ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙΛΙΚΗ; [about the true Author of which Book, the Earl of <hi>Anglesey,</hi> and (a Conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Divine) the Reverend Dr. <hi>Anthony Walker,</hi> and not I, must be an Informer unto as many as would be truly informed]; and unto this Proposal of our <hi>Vox Cleri,</hi> not I, but one who called himself, <hi>A sober Lay-man of the Church of England,</hi> hereupon Publishing a <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> hath answered, <hi>And why not the</hi> Arcadian Prayer <hi>in the same Book, for the furthering of our Devotions?</hi> What shall we say more? If nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Commands</hi> of Christ, nor the <hi>Judgments</hi> of God, nor the <hi>Arguments</hi> of the strongest Reason, with the long <hi>Experience</hi> of above an Hundred and fifty Years Nonsense in <hi>Imposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Persecutions,</hi> have not persuaded us to make a more thorough <hi>Reformation;</hi> one would think that the <hi>Derision,</hi> which for the want of it, we have had from the <hi>Papist,</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, whom it has been our pretence therein to accommodate, might have carried some lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle persuasion in it. Reader, unto them that are most concerned, let us leave the Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a very pungent Passage, which <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Weston</hi> hath, in his <hi>Theatrum Vitae Civilis &amp; Sacrae,</hi> Printed at <hi>Antwerp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alii</hi> Protestantes, <hi>ne prorsus Impii videantur, nostris</hi> Missali, <hi>ac</hi> Breviario, <hi>cum suo delectu utuntur. Et quò Religionis apud eos Forma cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brior appareat, adh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bent</hi> Canonicos, <hi>etiam, si diis
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:93774:46"/> placet, &amp;</hi> Archidiachonos. <hi>Adcoque de More</hi> Ecclesiae Romanae <hi>Eorum Cappas, pluvialia &amp;</hi> ejusdem Supellectiiem, <hi>quam dicunt invenisse in</hi> Synagoga Antichristi. <hi>Quo ipso liquet, Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Protestantium imprimis Furto noxiam — vel si Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s haberi r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant, maneant Simiae nostrae, &amp;</hi> Antichristi. <hi>Ridentur hi, cum omni suâ Scenâ, non à nostris modò, verùm &amp; à suis:</hi> And then he adds the saying of one, <hi>Videntur Angli Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam à suo Regno fugâsse adeò festinè, ut eum Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerint vestes à Tergo relinquere; quibus isti, Ovantium Ritu Choros ducentes, induuntur perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati.</hi> But none of all these considerations hath hitherto moved the <hi>Predominant Party;</hi> nor have these true Sons of <hi>Austin</hi> the Monk, taken any other methods to recommend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves unto the <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> than that old Formal and Foolish <hi>Monk</hi> took to push the Papal <hi>Ceremonies</hi> upon those ancient Churches of <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> our <hi>British</hi> Ancestors. The Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the beginning of the <hi>Commination against Sinners,</hi> does confess, That her <hi>Discipline</hi> is not so good as that of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches</hi> was for several Ages. And no <hi>Commination</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ against the <hi>Unreformable,</hi> has caused them to lay aside their sinful Resolution, <hi>That it never shall be so.</hi> The <hi>Reformation</hi> when carried but <hi>half through,</hi> immediately stuck like an <hi>Inchanted Cart,</hi> and if by any driving that hath made the <hi>tackling</hi> all fly, it hath been strain'd beyond the <hi>Line,</hi> where the <hi>Spell</hi> was first laid upon it, it hath soon resil'd within that <hi>Line</hi> again with a Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. Mow to use (which on this Theme (still choose) the words of a <hi>Conformable</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:93774:46"/> Writer, <hi>Is it not strange</hi> [saith the Conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Author of a <hi>Plea for Abatement] to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that in the Reformation of Religion, there should be so great a sally out of Darkness into mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Light upon the first dawning of that Day, and that notwithstanding all the Prayers and Tears of Oppressed Consciences, and the utmost endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of our Learned Fathers, it could not for more than this Hundred Years, be carried on one step fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther towards perfection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">§. 12. Thus it must be, because an <hi>Half time</hi> of the <hi>Twelve hundred and sixty years,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined for the continuance of the <hi>Apostacy,</hi> was yet behind. But now, <hi>lift up your heads</hi> ye Reforming Churches of God, <hi>because Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth nigh.</hi> The <hi>Hundred and four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score years</hi> are almost out; and then an irresisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit of <hi>REFORMATION</hi> showred from the Lord Jesus Christ on the Hearts of men, shall bring mighty and happy Changes upon the World. He doth great things by <hi>Spirit,</hi> and, <hi>Lord, I know that thou canst do every thing.</hi> The Sacred Oracles of Heaven assign <hi>Two steps</hi> to be taken for the abolishing of <hi>Antichrist:</hi> First an <hi>Harvest,</hi> and then a <hi>Vintage:</hi> Our Lord had a notable <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest</hi> of Churches gathered out of the <hi>Papal Empire</hi> at the <hi>Reformation</hi> in the former <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury;</hi> but the <hi>Harvest</hi> leaves no little work for the <hi>Vintage,</hi> which always comes about a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth part</hi> of the Year after it. Now the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth part of the <hi>Twelve hundred and sixty years,</hi> which constitute the grand year of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> is just an <hi>Hundred and fourscore</hi> Years; and about so many Years from the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:93774:47"/>
               <hi>Reformation,</hi> we shall see Popery <hi>cast into the great wine-press of the wrath of God.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in this <hi>Thorny Argument</hi> I have still cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen to say all in words whereto the <hi>Conformable</hi> Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have helped me, I will here choose to sum up my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the words of <hi>such an one;</hi> for <hi>such an one</hi> I find in the Year 1690, publickly thus expressing himself; <hi>It is the hope of many Good and Learned men, that the time is at hand when God will deliver his Church for ever from the darkness of the Kingdom of Antichrist; and that the Nations will cast away all things that have been Instruments of advancing his Tyranny and Superstition; surely that glorious Day will open mens Eyes; I have the faith to believe, that</hi> England <hi>will not be blind when other Nations do see.</hi> And long before him, I find another of <hi>them,</hi> namely, Dr. <hi>More</hi> saying, <hi>What harm is it to presage so well of the Reformation, as that after the Decursion of the years of their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, God will ripen them into a more manly sense of the great and indispensable Duties of the Gospel; That he will not tolerate nor connive any longer at their childish squabling about Nutshels, Counters, and Cherry-stones; but menace them even with Destruction, if they leave not off their Animosities and Asperities of mind about Trifles, and hold not fast unto the Royal Law of Love?</hi> I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach my Hand, if I did not find it even to <hi>tremble</hi> in Transcribing the terrible words of the Famous Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who hath Published this Prognostication: <hi>I think it exceeding proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that either</hi> England <hi>will have</hi> Popery <hi>settled
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:93774:47"/> in Power by a</hi> French Conquest, <hi>in the</hi> French Fashion, <hi>by the Compliance of those of the</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Clergy, <hi>who are for a</hi> Foreign Church-Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction, <hi>or else God will constrain the present Governors, by the sense of their own Interest, if not of the Interest of Religion and the common Good, to open the publick Church-doors unto that Concord, against which they have been lock'd by the Act of</hi> Uniformity, <hi>and such like, above Thirty Years; and the unplacable Enemies of Peace will cast down themselves.</hi> The former part of this terrible <hi>Prognostication,</hi> how probable so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Sins of men have rendred it, we may hope shall by the Sovereign <hi>Mercy</hi> of Heaven be prevented; but the latter part of it, shall by the Almighty <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, working on the Hearts of men, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever not without an amazing <hi>shake</hi> once more not only of the <hi>Earth,</hi> but of the <hi>Heavens</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, be speedily and gloriously accomplished.</p>
            <p>It would indeed make a Volume to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite all the <hi>hopeful passages</hi> of a true <hi>ELEU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERIAN</hi> strain, which we find oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in the Books of late Years, written by many <hi>Conformable</hi> Sons of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Now because I am going to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the <hi>Language,</hi> which will be heard through the Nation, when a wonderful <hi>Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> shall irresistibly bring on the heretofore maligned, and hitherto opposed <hi>Reformation;</hi> and Good men will write in all their Books, what was the <hi>Motto</hi> written by <hi>Selueccerus</hi> in all of his, ΠΕΡΙ ΠΑΝΤΟΣ ΤΗΝ ΕΛΕΓΘΕΡΙΑΝ. <hi>Above all things for LIBERTY.</hi> I am
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:93774:48"/> willing first of all to repeat a little of that <hi>Language,</hi> which I find in the Writings of the <hi>Conformable. Reader,</hi> Shall we go so high as the very Reverend old <hi>Robert Abbot</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> whose Two Younger Brothers, one became Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the other became Lord-Mayor of <hi>London?</hi> This great man, when Doctor of the Chair in the University of <hi>Oxford</hi> [1615.] thus expressed himself; <q rend="margSglQuotes">There are <hi>some,</hi> that are partly <hi>Romish,</hi> partly <hi>English,</hi> as occasion serves: So that a man may say unto them, <hi>Noster es, an Adversariorum?</hi> Who under pretence of <hi>Truth,</hi> and preaching against the <hi>Puritans,</hi> strike at the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> now Established among us. This Preaching against the <hi>Puritans,</hi> was but the practice of <hi>Parsons</hi> and <hi>Campion's</hi> Counsel <hi>[Two notorious Jesuites]</hi> when they came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England</hi> to seduce young Students: For when many of them were afraid they should lose their places if they should professedly be thus, the Counsel they then gave them was, <hi>That they should speak freely against the Puritans,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> should suffice. Now for this speech, That the <hi>Presbyterians are as bad as the Papists;</hi> there is a <hi>sting</hi> in it, which I wish had been left out; for there are many <hi>Churches beyond the Seas</hi> which contend for the <hi>Religion</hi> established amongst us, which yet have Approved and Admitted the <hi>Presbytery;</hi> and this is to make <hi>them</hi> as bad as the <hi>Papists.</hi> Besides, there have lived among us many Reverend and Worthy men, which have
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:93774:48"/> not rejected the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> taking it even for <hi>Lay Elders;</hi> and amongst the rest, Dr. <hi>Nowel,</hi> late Dean of <hi>Pauls,</hi> in his larger Catechism, <hi>p.</hi> 29. and 71. affirms, <hi>That in every well Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd Church there was a Presbytery;</hi> and yet this Catechism, by the late Reverend Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was commanded to be had in every <hi>Grammar-School;</hi> which surely he would not have done, if the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were as dangerous or bad as the <hi>Papists.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But I spoke of coming to the <hi>late Years,</hi> and I will do it as fast as I can. 'Tis Bishop <hi>Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> who says, <q rend="margSglQuotes">If you be free from the <hi>Rites</hi> that <hi>God</hi> himself once <hi>Prescribed,</hi> then are you free from the <hi>Traditions</hi> of <hi>men.</hi> It is a most <hi>wicked</hi> thing, that they should im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this <hi>Yoke</hi> upon you, and you are most <hi>foolish</hi> to submit your <hi>Necks</hi> unto it; for <hi>God</hi> would not have abolished the <hi>Ceremonial Law</hi> Instituted by <hi>himself,</hi> that a <hi>New One</hi> may be invented by <hi>men.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis Bishop <hi>Taylor</hi> who says, <q rend="margSglQuotes">
                  <hi>a symbolical Rite</hi> of <hi>Human Invention,</hi> to <hi>signify</hi> what it does not <hi>effect,</hi> and then introduced in the <hi>Solemn Service of God,</hi> is so like those <hi>vain</hi> Imaginations and Representations forbidden in the <hi>Second Commandment,</hi> that the very <hi>suspicion</hi> is more against <hi>Edification,</hi> than their use can pretend unto. <hi>Ecclesiastical Laws</hi> are to be fitted for the advantage of the Churches, Ministring to <hi>Edification,</hi> and complying with <hi>Charity;</hi> whatever <hi>Ecclesiastical Law</hi> hath not these Conditions, the <hi>Churches ought not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:93774:49"/>
            <p>'Tis Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> (one as worthy to have been a <hi>Bishop</hi> as Archbishop <hi>Laud</hi>) who says, <q rend="margSglQuotes">That when either <hi>False</hi> or <hi>Uncertain</hi> Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions are obtruded for <hi>Truth,</hi> or Acts either <hi>Unlawful</hi> or Ministring just <hi>Scruple,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us to be performed; in these ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, Consent were <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> and open <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation</hi> is not <hi>Faction</hi> or <hi>Schism,</hi> but due Christian <hi>Animosity.</hi> That it hath been the common <hi>Disease</hi> of Christians from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning not to content themselves with that <hi>measure of Faith,</hi> which God and the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> have expresly afforded. — But upon pretence of <hi>Church Authority</hi> (which is <hi>none</hi>) or <hi>Tradition</hi> (which for the most part is but <hi>feign'd</hi>) they have peremptorily concluded, and confidently imposed upon others, a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of entertaining Conclusions of that nature. That to load our <hi>publick Forms</hi> with the <hi>private Fancies</hi> upon which we differ, is the most Sovereign way to perpetuate <hi>Schism</hi> unto the worlds end. That they do but abuse themselves and others, that would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade us, that <hi>Bishops</hi> by Christ's Institution have any <hi>Superiority</hi> over other men, further than that of <hi>Reverence.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi> (one as worthy of a <hi>Bishoprick</hi> too as any other) who says, <q rend="margSglQuotes">
                  <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiformity</hi> in things merely indifferent, with mutual <hi>Charity,</hi> doth more promote God's Glory than <hi>Uniformity</hi> it self.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis Bishop <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> who says (though he were not a <hi>Bishop</hi> when he said it) <q rend="margSglQuotes">Let men turn and wind themselves which way
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:93774:49"/> they will, by the very same Arguments that any will prove <hi>Separation</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Lawful, because she required <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful things as conditions</hi> of her Communion, it will be proved Lawful, <hi>Not to conform to any suspected or unlawful Practice,</hi> required by any Church-Governors upon the <hi>same Terms,</hi> if the thing so required be after serious and sober enquiry, judged <hi>Unwarrantable</hi> by a man's own Conscience. <hi>Again,</hi> What possible reason can be given, why such things should not be sufficient for Communion with a Church, which are sufficient for <hi>Salvation?</hi> And certainly those things are sufficient for <hi>That,</hi> which are laid down as the <hi>necessary Duties of Christianity</hi> by our Lord and Saviour in his Word. — Without all Controversy, the main inlet of all the Distractions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions, and Divisions in the Christian World, hath been by <hi>Adding other Conditions of Church Communion than Christ hath made. Further,</hi> By allowing a <hi>Liberty</hi> for matters of <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency,</hi> and <hi>bearing</hi> with the <hi>weak,</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear things which others count <hi>Lawful,</hi> we might indeed be restored unto a <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Lustre</hi> far sooner, than by furbishing up some Antiquated <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their Pedigree no higher, than from some ancient Custom and Tradition.</q>
               <hi>Once more,</hi>
               <q rend="margSglQuotes">There is nothing the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> deserves greater Imitation by us in, than that admirable Temper, Moderation, and Condescention, which was used in it towards all the Members of it. It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:93774:50"/> thought worth the while to make any standing Laws for <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Customs,</hi> that had no other Original but <hi>Tradition,</hi> much less to suspend men her <hi>Communion</hi> for not observing them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis the Bishop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> who says, <q rend="margSglQuotes">As long as men hold fast the <hi>Body</hi> of Christ, be not Rigorous with them for <hi>Shadows.</hi> This Forceable urging <hi>Uniformity</hi> in <hi>Worship,</hi> hath caused great division in <hi>Faith</hi> as well as <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> I beseech you in the fear of God, set before your Eyes the dreadful <hi>Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> when Christ on his Tribunal of Justice shall thus question you, <hi>Are</hi> your <hi>Ceremonies more dear unto you, than the Souls for which I Died? If</hi> David <hi>dispensed with a Ceremony Commanded by God to satisfy the Hunger of his People, Will not you dispense with your own Ceremonies to satisfy the Souls of my People? Shall they perish for transgressing your</hi> Human Laws, <hi>which they ignorantly conclude Erroneous, and shall not you perish for transgressing my</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Laws, <hi>which you know to be Good and Holy?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis the <hi>Protestant Reconciler</hi> (a faithful Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as one calls him) who says, <q rend="margSglQuotes">It is certain that our Church hath altered her <hi>Liturgy</hi> at several <hi>Times,</hi> and in several <hi>Parts.</hi> Hence it appears, how sense<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly 'tis alledged, That we cannot <hi>abate these Ceremonies,</hi> because they have been <hi>once</hi> received by the Church. One skill'd in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity</hi> will be convinced of the great <hi>insin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity</hi> of these two pretences; That we, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:93774:50"/> aside of the rest, have kept our present <hi>Ceremonies</hi> out of due Reverence to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis the Reverend Mr. <hi>Samuel Bolde,</hi> who says, <q rend="margSglQuotes">I dare affirm, That if the Rites and Ceremonies now in use in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> should be Altered by the same Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which did at first Enjoin them, the Church of <hi>England</hi> would still be as impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable a Bulwark against <hi>Popery</hi> as now she is; and I am fully satisfied there is no man will deny this, unless he be either a <hi>Real Papist,</hi> or an Ignorant and a Superstitious Fool.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Why should I quote the Four Books, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, <hi>The Conformists Plea for the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> which were Composed by a <hi>Beneficed Minister, and Regular Son of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and exposed in the Years 1681, 1682, 1683? Unto these, if I should add all that occurs in the <hi>several Arguments humbly Proposed for Concessions and Alterations in the Common-Prayer, and in the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of</hi> England (with numberless Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations from Conformable Authors therein made) published by a <hi>Minister of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as by Law Established,</hi> in the Year 1689. Some fierce <hi>IDUMAEAN</hi> would say, I am raising an <hi>Army</hi> of Moderate <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists</hi> against his <hi>Violent Party.</hi> And yet I must presume to Cite a few Lines out of the Author last mentioned: Says he, <q rend="margSglQuotes">The <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> are <hi>Inutilia Caelo,</hi> of little or no use for the <hi>winning of Souls.</hi> And I see not but that Prelate's Speech was truly Christian,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:93774:51"/> who said, <hi>We had rather lose a Ceremony than a Soul.</hi> As is said of some Meats, <hi>Neither if we Eat them are we the better, nor if we Eat not are we the worse;</hi> so we are nothing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by these <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> And the Reason for the use of the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> ceaseth much; they were kept partly out of Compliance with the <hi>Papists</hi> to gain upon <hi>them,</hi> but now the <hi>Papists</hi> are harden'd by it, upbraiding us (as Bishop <hi>Usher</hi> said of them) <hi>If our Flesh be not good, Why do you drink of our Broth?</hi> And the <hi>Conformists</hi> (many of them) would think it hard to be <hi>Silenc'd</hi> for not Assenting to the <hi>Perseverance of the Saints,</hi> or any other the <hi>Five Points,</hi> according to the common Sense of our <hi>Dissenting Brethren.</hi> — I shall conclude with the common Assertion of the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> That all <hi>Churches</hi> should labour as much as possibly may be, after <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical Simplicity,</hi> and fewness of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which they judge the safest, the purest, and the best; as <hi>Peter Martyr, Bucer, Calvin, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, Zanchy,</hi> and indeed almost all Good men affirm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Lest my Reader should grow <hi>weary</hi> [and yet who can be <hi>weary!</hi>] of being enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd with too long a <hi>Repetition</hi> of the true <hi>ELEUTHERIAN</hi> Language, to be found in the Books of many <hi>Conformable</hi> Writers, I will only Extract a few Lines from <hi>Two</hi> more of those Writers, who yet have not prefixed their <hi>Names</hi> unto their <hi>Works;</hi> and it is a shame to the Nation, that men who write so <hi>well,</hi> should find it necessary,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:93774:51"/> for the avoiding of <hi>Envy,</hi> to write <hi>Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was in the Year 1690, that one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Divine [whose Name, I hear, is Mr. <hi>Graves</hi>] Published a Discourse on the <hi>Vanity, Mischief, and Danger of continuing Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in the Worship of God:</hi> And now see what he says; <q rend="margSglQuotes">If we by continuing the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>Terms of Communion,</hi> drive People from us, the <hi>Schism</hi> will lodge at our doors, and we shall be the <hi>Schismaticks.</hi> They that for <hi>Rites</hi> labour to keep up our Animosities, make themselves Guilty of all the <hi>Persecutions of former Times;</hi> and God may charge upon them all the <hi>Righteous Blood</hi> that has been shed, from the Blood of <hi>Abel</hi> to the Blood of <hi>Russel; Verily I say unto you, it shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of this generation.</hi> — There is no keeping up the Honour of the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> except we <hi>blind</hi> the <hi>People,</hi> which is now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible. — Many of our own <hi>Clergy</hi> submit not unto them out of <hi>Choice,</hi> but as a <hi>Burthen</hi> from which they would gladly be delivered. — As <hi>Knowledge</hi> increaseth, <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>Ceremonies</hi> will grow more and more <hi>Ridiculous.</hi> — The Lords, the Knights of the Shires, and the Burgesses, know who are <hi>fit</hi> in their several Countries to be <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellors of Peace,</hi> and <hi>Healers of our Breaches;</hi> and if <hi>we</hi> are unwilling to be <hi>Peace-makers, they</hi> may (if they please) make a <hi>Law,</hi> That the <hi>Members of both Houses,</hi> shall in their several Countries, chuse Three or Four Divines to sit in <hi>Convocation</hi> to offer unto
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:93774:52"/> them, what may settle the Peace of our Church. — The <hi>Church</hi> would lose no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing though all its <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were laid aside. They are no more an <hi>Ornament</hi> unto the <hi>Church,</hi> than the <hi>Chains</hi> of a <hi>Galley</hi> or a <hi>Prison,</hi> are <hi>Ornaments</hi> to the poor man that is laden with them. — A Soul swallowed up in the Contemplations of the Infinite Majesty of the Glorious God, may reckon these imposed <hi>Fooleries,</hi> no better than the <hi>Fools-Caps</hi> and <hi>Coats</hi> which Persecutors did put on the Saints of God; they may be valued by formal <hi>Dead Christians,</hi> but the <hi>Spiritually Minded</hi> will look on them, as <hi>Toys</hi> fit only to Adorn <hi>Hypocrites.</hi> No man can shew any <hi>good</hi> they have done, except it be <hi>good</hi> to maintain a <hi>Corrupt Party</hi> in Church and State, to the excluding a <hi>Pious, Sober, Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, Diligent, Powerful</hi> Interest. <hi>Uniformity</hi> is <hi>Deformity,</hi> and Confusion, when men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point <hi>other Terms</hi> of Ministerial Service and Church-Communion, than are prescribed in <hi>God's Word.</hi> — The good Temper, Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Diligence, Faithfulness, and Courage of God's Servants, hath been useful to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; but a <hi>Carnal Faction of Christians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurried by a mad Zeal for little things, have oppressed these <hi>Benefactors,</hi> stained the Glory of the Nation, beaten down the Rents of Lands, discouraged Industry, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed Trade, and brought the most Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious <hi>Island</hi> in the World, unto a low state. — The making <hi>unnecessary Terms</hi> of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterial Service, which Christ never enjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:93774:52"/> is an Invasion of his <hi>Kingly Office.</hi> — Instead of keeping out <hi>Burning and Shining Lights,</hi> we had need <hi>Trim</hi> some of our own, which give but a <hi>faint Light,</hi> if any at all. — The most Learned <hi>Divines,</hi> and the Wisest <hi>Statesmen</hi> in the World, are but Bunglers when they take upon them to add unto <hi>God's Worship</hi> what he hath not appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. — With these Inventions <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Atheists</hi> are habited like <hi>Christians</hi> for the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the <hi>Devil,</hi> to corrupt and destroy true <hi>Christianity.</hi> — Mankind hath for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages been possessed and tormented with a <hi>furious Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> of <hi>Impositions;</hi> it will never be well till this <hi>Spirit</hi> is cast out. — <hi>Piety</hi> hath been hid in Corners, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move <hi>Stumbling-Blocks,</hi> and it will come forth and appear in publick with all its Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Glory. — The use of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> tends to the oppression of the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Christianity.</hi> They are like <hi>Painted Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,</hi> which make a gaudy shew, but they much lessen the <hi>Light.</hi> — The <hi>Carnal part</hi> of the world is easily engaged for <hi>them,</hi> against <hi>Holiness;</hi> and to such a degree that <hi>serious Piety</hi> hath been scoffed at, not only by the <hi>Mobile,</hi> but even the Tribe of the <hi>Long Robe</hi> when engaged to be <hi>Advocates for Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions.</hi> — Our furious <hi>Bigots,</hi> when they had quite trampled under foot the <hi>Dissenters,</hi> they began a wild Carier against Piety and Sobriety in their <hi>own Body.</hi> The Removal of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> will take away the <hi>Vizor</hi> with which <hi>Formalists, Hypocrites,</hi> Wicked and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:93774:53"/> Profane men, do cover themselves. The continuance of them in the Worship of God, will be a Gratification of the <hi>Worst</hi> of Christians, and a Grief to the <hi>Best.</hi> — It cannot be proved, that <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship ever did any <hi>good.</hi> — In the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> in the last Century, the <hi>Pope</hi> was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hence in such haste, that he left some of his <hi>Toys</hi> behind him; these have continued too long among us, to the great disturbance of the Church. In the first <hi>Reformation</hi> we were cleansed from <hi>Idolatry;</hi> in the <hi>next,</hi> I hope, we shall go a <hi>step further.</hi> — Let us not <hi>Fight against God;</hi> all dividing <hi>Terms of Communion,</hi> or of the Exercise of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, are the things to be removed in order to a <hi>more perfect Reformation</hi> of the Church, and to make way for a more holy and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed State; which may be at hand, if by our perverseness we do not put away this happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness from us: <hi>God is doing this Work in the World;</hi> it <hi>shall go on,</hi> though we perish by our foolish Obstinacy. — <hi>All</hi> the Pious, Sober, and Moderate Clergymen are for an <hi>Union;</hi> the rest are, some of them, <hi>Dignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Drones;</hi> these fear Contempt if more diligent Labourers are admitted into the Church. Some are <hi>Learned,</hi> but are infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a <hi>Pharisaical Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Form of Godliness,</hi> denying the <hi>Power</hi> thereof: Some are <hi>Debauch'd,</hi> and fear the <hi>severe Correction</hi> that is due unto them: Some are departed from our <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and fear <hi>(here the Shoe pincheth)</hi> that their <hi>Errors</hi> will be exposed by
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:93774:53"/> the Accession of such an <hi>Orthodox Interest,</hi> as the Body of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who are firm to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Some are so <hi>Sottish,</hi> that they act their part very ill, and would be undone if their <hi>Tools</hi> were taken away: All our Sticklers are <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivees</hi> for their own Humours, and care not what becomes of our <hi>Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties.</hi> — Though by the <hi>Act of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> the <hi>Instruments of Persecution</hi> are struck out of the hands of <hi>Persecutors,</hi> yet we may be still guilty of <hi>Persecution,</hi> if we continue <hi>those things</hi> that armed Evil men against the People of God. — He requires you to <hi>Pray unto the Lord of the harvest, that he would send forth more labourers into his harvest;</hi> and you keep away many worthy <hi>Labourers</hi> from his Work, because they cannot comply with Terms that he never appointed. —</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus he.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was in the Year 1693. That another <hi>Conformable</hi> Divine [whose Name as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed is Mr. <hi>Snowden</hi>] Published a Discourse <hi>for Abatement in Matters of Conformity to several Injunctions and Orders of the Church of</hi> England. See what he says: <q rend="margSglQuotes">
                  <hi>Compulsion</hi> is a Quiver which affords many a sharp <hi>Arrow,</hi> but such as seldom hit the Mark. — Yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go to the House of God in Company: How happy were it if the <hi>Partition Wall</hi> were broken down, or so <hi>wide a Door</hi> made in it that we might go in and out; that every thing were <hi>cut off</hi> which <hi>troubles</hi> the Church,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:93774:54"/> and which are as <hi>Goads</hi> in the Side, and <hi>Thorns</hi> in the Eye, of <hi>Conscience.</hi> The Convocation held in the Year 1640. speaking of the Custom of <hi>Bowing</hi> in token of Reverence to God when we come in the <hi>Place</hi> of Publick Worship, says thus; <hi>In the Practice or Admission of this Rite, we desire that the Rule of Charity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed by the Apostle may be observed, which is, That they who use this Rite, despise not those who use it not; and they who use it not, condemn not them who use it.</hi> (The like Liberty is left as to <hi>Bowing</hi> at the Name of <hi>Jesus</hi>). And I cannot understand, why the same <hi>Latitude</hi> or <hi>Charity</hi> might not be granted in the other scrupled parts of <hi>Conformity.</hi> The Church (I am of Opinion) may thank her <hi>Preferments</hi> for the extreme Zeal of many of her Votaries in the case of <hi>Conformity.</hi> The Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> never wanted Pledgers, whenever she drank to them out of her <hi>Golden Cup,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Abominations</hi> 'twas filled with. — Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose some of our Tackling should be rent, and Sprucery sullied, yet it were a Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune no way comparable to that of dashing the <hi>Ship</hi> against the <hi>Rock.</hi> And what <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack</hi> the Storms which some <hi>Zealots</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us are ever upon the least Alteration of that <hi>Rigging</hi> (though upon the justest Reasons) raising, may occasion, God only knows, if he that stills the <hi>Raging of the Sea,</hi> does not quiet the <hi>Madness of the People.</hi> — Why might not things be so tempered, that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by hearkening to some <hi>Terms</hi> of accommodation, and making a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:93774:54"/> Rebatement of <hi>Disputable Things,</hi> and (all along) offensive <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more enlarged, and settled upon a firmer <hi>Basis</hi> and more <hi>tried Foundation?</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I have some good reason to know, and <hi>believe</hi> (and <hi>therefore do I speak</hi>) that many of our Dissenting Brethren be of <hi>Mephibosheth</hi>'s mind, That if the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> may be secured, the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> setled in Peace, they are contented the <hi>Ziba</hi>'s should <hi>take all;</hi> they grudge not at their <hi>Preferments</hi> and <hi>Dignities.</hi> — But why should we <hi>envy</hi> our <hi>Brethrens</hi> sitting at the <hi>same Table,</hi> when we have all the <hi>same Faith,</hi> the <hi>same Father,</hi> the <hi>same Baptism,</hi> and the <hi>same hope of our Calling?</hi> Or, Is there no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to be had unto the <hi>tender Consciences</hi> of <hi>Conformists,</hi> who rather than violate the <hi>Peace,</hi> or break the <hi>Unity</hi> of the Church, have a <hi>long time laboured under an heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then?</hi> I wish there may not be the same rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to believe now, what a Reverend Doctor and Dignitary of the Church hath some Years since declared unto the World, <hi>That they seem resolved to break all in pieces, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard our Religion, and let these sad effects, our Divisions, still continue, than to abate their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour in Imposing, what they may Lawfully Alter and Abolish.</hi> The <hi>Old Leven</hi> could not be <hi>purged out</hi> all at once; and therefore several of the greatest Prelates in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Days endeavoured to proceed in that work; but <hi>Satan hindred them;</hi> and, <hi>he that hath let, still lets;</hi> yea, that <hi>Mystery of Iniquity will
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:93774:55"/> work, till it be taken out of the way.</hi> — While our <hi>Discipline</hi> hath been very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sighted in matters of <hi>Conformity</hi> as to the smallest <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> it hath been comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dull in hearing, and slow in spying the greatest <hi>Immoralities.</hi> — We should all sit under our <hi>Vines</hi> and <hi>Fig-trees,</hi> leading a <hi>peaceable and quiet life,</hi> when once these <hi>Apples of Strife</hi> (which, they say, grow upon a <hi>Tree</hi> that is neither <hi>Good</hi> nor <hi>Evil</hi>) became <hi>Forbidden Fruit. Haec ille</hi> —</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Reader,</hi> I am so far from able to brag, with old <hi>Epicurus,</hi> of not having in all my Writings <hi>Quoted</hi> any <hi>one</hi> single Authority out of any <hi>Book</hi> whatsoever, that (although I have not, as <hi>Pineda</hi> did in his <hi>Monarchia Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastica,</hi> Cited One thousand and forty Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors) I doubt I have brought some <hi>Quotations,</hi> enough offensive to some that have more of <hi>Epicurus</hi> than of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> in their <hi>Divinity;</hi> and that stick at nothing to maintain their <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Monarchy.</hi> But as Mr. <hi>Samuel Bolde</hi> (a <hi>Conformist</hi>) hath reported, That a <hi>Church-Warden</hi> having Presented a Person unto the <hi>Ecclesiastical Court,</hi> one in the Court immediately applied himself unto the <hi>Register,</hi> saying, <hi>What do you mean? You'll spoil all; for this Gentleman is ONE OF US; he will swear and be Drunk as well as the BEST OF US:</hi> Say you so, quoth the Register, <hi>Then the Case is altered;</hi> and immediately cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the <hi>Church-Warden,</hi> he told him, <hi>he was a most impudent and villanous Rakehel to Present so
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:93774:55"/> worthy a Gentleman,</hi> and chid him sharply for it. Even so, when we <hi>Nonconformists</hi> meet with any man who desires the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> to be carried on by the <hi>Rules</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, as the Blessed men that first <hi>attempted</hi> it, <hi>intended</hi> it; or, who carries the heart of a true <hi>Englishman</hi> in him, for the <hi>Constitution</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> with the Principles which alone can maintain the late <hi>happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution;</hi> or who is for <hi>Government</hi> without <hi>Slavery,</hi> in <hi>Spirituals</hi> or <hi>Temporals;</hi> we must be excused if we presently cry out, <hi>This is ONE OF US;</hi> and though he may be a <hi>Conformist,</hi> yet make <hi>bold</hi> freely to Quote him as <hi>OUR OWN.</hi> For I do again say, the <hi>difference</hi> between us will, by a wonderful Work of Heaven upon the Nation, be quickly taken away; <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Hooper</hi> will quickly <hi>shake Hands;</hi> and our <hi>Brethren [for we are Brethren]</hi> among the <hi>Conformable</hi> in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> will now <hi>quickly</hi> come to speak the Language exemplified in the Citations thus made from <hi>some</hi> of them: They will speak as the Learned <hi>Crakenthorp</hi> did for the <hi>Puritans</hi> in the former Age, <hi>In Doctrinâ &amp; Fidei Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxae professione Discordia inter nos nulla; Hâc integrâ, in Ritibus &amp; Discipliná, Discrimen fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum, utrique Scimus.</hi> We are one in <hi>Faith,</hi> and it's no matter whether we be one in <hi>Rite</hi> or no. Yea, they will speak it in so general and so prevailing a Note, That the <hi>wicked who will be grieved at it, shall gnash their teeth and melt away:</hi> Nor shall the Sons of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crustes</hi> be able to hinder this <hi>Restoration</hi> of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:93774:56"/> Mankind unto its <hi>Liberty.</hi> That part of the <hi>English Nation</hi> which values its true <hi>English Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> (for which, if <hi>the Heavens were Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Seas were Ink,</hi> as the <hi>Rabbi</hi> says, they would not suffice to write the just Praises of God), I say, that part of the <hi>English Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> will not much longer permit the truest Friends of <hi>English Liberty</hi> to be suppressed, Abused, and Incapacitated, merely to please the Humours of a <hi>Faction,</hi> who have always done all they can to betray that <hi>English Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> A glorious King will set himself to put an <hi>effectual stop unto the Profanity and Immorality which have depraved the Kingdoms;</hi> and he will unite the <hi>Best People in the Nation,</hi> to assist that Best of Undertakings. A Senator invited <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> unto a Feast; whereto as the Emperor was coming, he heard an horrid cry of a wretched man, whom he saw a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany dragging after them: The Emperor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the cause of that Violence, it was answered, <hi>Their Master had Condemned him to the Fish-ponds for Breaking a Glass which he set a high Value upon;</hi> whereupon he Commanded a stay of the Execution, until he arrived at the House of the Senator; where the Senator shewed him a Room well furnished with <hi>Glas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> whereof he Valued some at the <hi>Price of a Province:</hi> The Emperor saw they were <hi>pretty things,</hi> but he saw that they were likely to be the cause of abundance of Mischief, and therefore uttering that Expression <hi>Better all these perish than one man,</hi> he presently <hi>broke them all to Pieces.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:93774:56"/>
            <p>Our <hi>Caesar,</hi> and the most powerful Friends of our <hi>Caesar,</hi> will shortly pass the like righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doom upon those <hi>wretched things,</hi> which by being made <hi>the Terms of Communion,</hi> have really proved <hi>the Grounds of Separation</hi> between the <hi>Best People in the Nation.</hi> Such they have <hi>really proved,</hi> and such they will <hi>still,</hi> and <hi>ever</hi> prove, until Men are so <hi>Wise</hi> and <hi>Just,</hi> as to take them away: For 'tis truly observed by a Person of no mean <hi>consideration,</hi> and of some <hi>Conformity</hi> too, <hi>That should the Nation be at once emptied of one whole Generation of Nonconformists, so long as the reading of the Bible is suffered, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will unavoidably and immediately spring up.</hi> But when this <hi>Day of Coalition</hi> shall come, it will bring on the most glorious Times that ever arose upon the <hi>English Horizon;</hi> and as the <hi>Curse</hi> of our JESUS will fall, as it hath already fallen, upon the Persons and Houses of them who have assay'd the rebuilding of the <hi>Old</hi> Romish <hi>Jericho,</hi> which hath been so far there demolished; so in the room thereof there shall be introduced a <hi>New Jerusalem.</hi> THEN, <hi>the Dukes of Edom shall be amazed.</hi> And that in this Expectation also, I may not seem carried away with mere <hi>Fanaticism</hi> and <hi>Enthusiasm,</hi> I will take the leave to make one Quotation more from a <hi>Conformable</hi> Divine: 'Tis Dr. <hi>Drue Cressener,</hi> who in the Year 1687. upon the Occasion of the late King's <hi>Declaration</hi> for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> wrote the following words: <hi>The present Revolutions, I look upon to be the beginning of the Preparations for the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Kingdom of Christ upon the Earth. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:93774:57"/> others may intend or design by the</hi> Liberty of Conscience, <hi>I cannot believe that it will ever be recall'd in</hi> England <hi>as long as the World stands. The next Year seems in all probability to be a Year of Wonders, for the Recovery of the Church. — And I send you the News of a continual Increase of the flourishing State of the Church very shortly to begin, and to continue unto the End of the World.</hi> In fine, As the first pretended <hi>Statute</hi> that ever was in <hi>England,</hi> for the <hi>vexing</hi> of Christians on the account of Religion, by the colour whereof the <hi>Bishops</hi> committed great Oppressions and Cruelties, was one that never pass'd the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> but the <hi>House of Commons</hi> in the next <hi>Parliament,</hi> with the concurrence of the <hi>King,</hi> vehemently protested against it, albeit the then <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> with the help of the other <hi>Prelates,</hi> found a way unjustly to suppress and conceal the <hi>Revocation</hi> of that pretended <hi>Statute;</hi> so it may be hoped our Lord Jesus Christ will bless the Nation with <hi>Parliaments</hi> that shall restrain a <hi>Corrupt Clergy,</hi> not only from <hi>vexing</hi> of Christians on the account of <hi>Religion,</hi> but also from stopping any more the progress of <hi>Religion</hi> in the Nation. THEN, <hi>Thus saith the Lord God, concerning</hi> EDOM; <hi>The pride of thine heart hath deceived thee; thou whose habitation is high, that saith in his heart, Who shall bring me down to the ground? Tho thou exalt thy self as the eagle, and tho thou set thy nest among the stars, thence will I bring thee down, saith the Lord. — Saviours shall come upon mount Zion, to judge the mount of Esau, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms shall be the Lords.</hi> What shall I say? The
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:93774:57"/>
               <hi>Spirit</hi> of Christ sent forth at the <hi>Reformation,</hi> an <hi>Hundred and fourscore</hi> Years ago, carried back some Advice, That the <hi>Deluge</hi> of Popish Ignorance, and Wickedness, and Wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, was <hi>abated from off the earth.</hi> But that <hi>Spirit</hi> is going to be again sent forth, and it will remain here, without leaving this woful World, as it hath heretofore done; for behold, <hi>The face of the earth will quickly be dry before it.</hi> Then the <hi>Spirit of Christ</hi> shall no longer be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably distinguish'd from the <hi>Spirit of the Church;</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi>'s Complaint shall no more be made, <hi>Sunt nunc homines, magis vindictae cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidi, magis avari, magis ab omni misericordiâ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moti, magis immodesti, &amp; indisciplinati, multoque deteriores, quam fuerunt sub Papatu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">§. 13. Indeed those Dispensations of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that shall bring on the <hi>Reformation</hi> and the <hi>Resurrection</hi> of the <hi>European</hi> Churches, can be no other than <hi>Constellations</hi> of <hi>Miracles.</hi> But fear not, O ye Disciples, whose <hi>Faith</hi> is almost sunk in the Storms which threaten to overwhelm that <hi>Bark</hi> which hath the Interests of One infinitely greater than <hi>Caesar</hi> in the bottom of it: An <hi>Age of Miracles</hi> is now dawning upon the World; and
<q xml:lang="lat">Fluctuat, at nunquam mergitur illa ratis.</q> Proper <hi>Miracles</hi> were continued in the Church of God, for Two or Three Hundred Years together, even until the <hi>Antichristian Apostacy</hi> was come on to some extremity. And whether
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:93774:58"/> there may not be a Return of those <hi>powers of the world to come,</hi> when the <hi>Apostacy</hi> shall be over, is known unto the <hi>Lord of that world.</hi> Such <hi>Miracles</hi> have been lately wrought, more than two or three of them, in the City of <hi>London,</hi> as well as elsewhere: Persons who have had their <hi>Limbs</hi> miserably disjointed, Persons that have had inveterate <hi>Palsies,</hi> incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Fistulaes,</hi> desperate <hi>Leprosies;</hi> these Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as they have been reading the Ancient <hi>Miracles</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Christ hath wonderfully given them the <hi>Faith</hi> of his doing the like for them; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! they have to the astonishment of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, been by the like <hi>Miracles</hi> perfectly and presently recover'd out of all their Maladies. If the Relations and Evidences that we have of these <hi>Great Things</hi> had not been incontesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I would not have mention'd them: Now say I, <hi>That the Lord's Name</hi> (that is, <hi>his Christ) is near, his wondrous works declare.</hi> I make no doubt that these may be <hi>Symbolical</hi> Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Exhibitions of the <hi>Great Things</hi> which the <hi>Miraculous</hi> Providence of our Lord Jesus Christ is going to do for his People in the World. After a very deliberate Meditation and Inquisition upon the Divine Oracles, and after utmost Application to those Methods by which one may arrive to any <hi>understanding in the Times,</hi> I do humbly affirm, That we may <hi>understand by Books</hi> the <hi>Number of Years</hi> allotted for the Church's lying under its <hi>Desolations,</hi> to be very near unto its Accomplishment. And this <hi>Book</hi> of mine does now appear among
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:93774:58"/> you, ye faithful People of God, with <hi>Good Tidings of great Joy,</hi> even the <hi>Tidings</hi> of a REVOLUTION and a REFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MATION <hi>at the very Door,</hi> which will be vastly more <hi>wonderful</hi> than any of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances</hi> yet seen by the Church of God from the beginning of the World. Yea, if this <hi>Book</hi> were capable of carrying the Advice as far as the Voice of the <hi>Seventh Apocalyptical Trumpet</hi> (which we may be sure must <hi>sound quickly</hi>) shall be extended, it should carry this Advice, <hi>The Kingdom of God is at hand.</hi> The precise <hi>Year</hi> for the great <hi>Revolution,</hi> I do not pretend so much as to <hi>conjecture;</hi> but that the <hi>Time is at hand,</hi> I venture to utter as a thing beyond <hi>Conjecture.</hi> We all know, <hi>Glorious things are spoken of thee, O thou city of God!</hi> I say not that these things will come on without such horrible Commotions, and Concussions, and Confusions, that <hi>mens hearts every where shall fail them for fear, and for looking after those things which are coming on the earth.</hi> The mighty <hi>Angels</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ will make their descent, and set the World a <hi>trembling</hi> at the Approaches of their Almighty Lord: They will <hi>shake</hi> Churches, and <hi>shake</hi> Nations, and <hi>shake</hi> Empires, and <hi>shake</hi> mighty King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and <hi>shake once more not Earth only, but Heaven also.</hi> And the <hi>Great SWORD</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by <hi>Lactantius,</hi> to <hi>fall from Heaven to Earth,</hi> when the <hi>Lord of the Celestial Armies is at hand,</hi> will fill both Pages of all <hi>Gazettes</hi> with <hi>Armies,</hi> and <hi>Campaigns,</hi> and <hi>Sieges,</hi> and horrendous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solations. But this is to be expected, That
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:93774:59"/> the <hi>Day is at hand,</hi> when <hi>the kingdoms of this world shall become the kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Christ:</hi> Even the Day when <hi>Rome,</hi> with all its <hi>Unreformable</hi> Adherents and Supporters, will not only see fulfill'd the Prophecy of her own <hi>Irish Malachi, Civitas Septi-collis diruetur, &amp; judex tremendus judicabit populum suum;</hi> but shall also suffer all the <hi>Plagues</hi> threatned her <hi>in a more sure word of prophecy.</hi> And shall not an early and an happy Share in the <hi>Holy Changes</hi> that are coming upon the World, be enjoy'd by <hi>Great Britain,</hi> the Island which was irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diated with the Gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ, several Years before the chiefest Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s being at <hi>Rome,</hi> durst pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose his Arrival there, even according to the Assertion of the Ancient <hi>Gildas, Tempore ut scimus summo Tiberii Caesaris, Radios suos primum indulget, id est, praecepta, Christus:</hi> We know Christ granted his <hi>Rays</hi> to this Land first, in the latter end of <hi>Tiberius Caesar,</hi> whose last Year was the <hi>Thirty seventh</hi> of our Lord? There is no little <hi>reason to be given for such an hope.</hi> The Omnipotent Lord Jesus Christ, who manages the <hi>Isles as a very little thing,</hi> even as a Man does the <hi>Spittle</hi> in his Mouth [for so the <hi>Seventy</hi> render that Passage] giving it whatever <hi>Turn,</hi> and whatever <hi>Cast</hi> he pleaseth, hath marvellous Things to do in <hi>Great Britain;</hi> yea, upon those <hi>Islands</hi> his <hi>people shall renew their strength;</hi> and the unreasonable and Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical TESTS that have enfeebled them, will be taken off. Now as <hi>Judas Maccabaeus,</hi> after the Prophanation of the <hi>Mosaical</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:93774:59"/> by <hi>Antiochus</hi> [who some say was the <hi>first</hi> that ever invaded <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> and I add, a <hi>Type</hi> of the <hi>Last;</hi>] for <hi>Twelve hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and sixty</hi> Natural Days, then spent <hi>Thirty Days</hi> in the <hi>Purification</hi> of the Temple, and spent <hi>Forty five</hi> Days more to prepare all things for the <hi>Dedication</hi> of it; so 'tis not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that when the <hi>Twelve hundred and sixty Years</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> are out, there may go some Years to <hi>sweep</hi> and <hi>cleanse</hi> the Church of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>wrong things</hi> that are crept into it; and then comes the <hi>End,</hi> which <hi>blessed is he that waits and comes unto.</hi> But the Days of <hi>Purifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> are hastning upon the Church, wherein the <hi>Temple</hi> will be <hi>swept</hi> and <hi>cleansed</hi> from the things that have hitherto defiled it; and tho' there should then be found in <hi>England</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, any considerable Persons guilty of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi>'s fault, who undertook the Patronage of the Abuses in the beginning of the <hi>Fifth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury,</hi> against which <hi>Vigilantius</hi> appeared, and who bestow'd the name of <hi>Dormitantius,</hi> with other base and bad Language upon that <hi>Man of God;</hi> yet such <hi>vigilant</hi> Servants of God, as become vigorous <hi>Reformers</hi> of the Abuses now prevailing, shall be gloriously prospered. Sirs! You are not now to be discourag'd with an <hi>Abi in cellam, &amp; dic, miserere mei Deus:</hi> 'Tis <hi>Time</hi> for you to be at work, even at the Work of <hi>publishing</hi> to the Church of God, those Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Evangelical <hi>Truth,</hi> whereto it should be more <hi>conformed.</hi> Let the <hi>Witnesses</hi> of our Lord, who have hitherto been Preaching un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Cross,</hi> now set themselves to extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:93774:60"/>
               <hi>Prayer,</hi> with <hi>Fasting,</hi> like the Devotions of <hi>Daniel</hi> before the Lord; and in the solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est way often resigning themselves up to the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of God, that being possessed by him, they may be fitted for, and used in the most eminent <hi>Services:</hi> Let them <hi>then</hi> study what <hi>Services</hi> they would have the Lord Jesus Christ at his coming, find them engaged in. You are going to drop off your <hi>Sackcloth,</hi> ye <hi>Elijahs;</hi> the <hi>Old Cloaths</hi> of the <hi>Wilderness</hi> will be taken from you sooner than you are aware; and you shall have the <hi>garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Luther,</hi> with the other <hi>Heroes</hi> of his Time, had been apprehensive that the <hi>Time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi> for making better and hotter Batteries than those which <hi>Huss</hi> and others had an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years before made upon the <hi>Romish Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> was come on, what <hi>Security</hi> would have been added unto their <hi>Magnanimity?</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Est ventura Dies, Romae quae subruat Arces;</l>
               <l>Jam quassae nutant Turres, Lapsumque minantur.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:93774:60"/>
            <head>The Conformists Reasons for hearing and joining with the Nonconformists.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THE same Reasons which oblige Persons to hear and join with us, oblige us also to take all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of hearing and join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Nonconformists, they being Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of Christ, having due Call and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from him to preach the Gospel. The Church hath real need of their Labours, their Ministry is hated by Satan and his Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; they are duly subject to the higher Powers, and are protected by the Law of the Land in the course of their Ministry, and are a considerable part of that same Church of <hi>England,</hi> which His present Majesty under God is Supreme Governor of, according to the old Oath of Supremacy, and the 37th Article of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Those Words of our Saviour's take place here; <hi>He that is not against us, is on our part, Mark</hi> 9.40. The Nonconformists <hi>really</hi> are not against us, therefore they are on our part. The Scope and Drift of their Ministry is to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:93774:61"/> win Souls, not to this or that Sect, but to Christ; to teach them their Duty to God, and to His present Majesty, as sole Supreme under God, and the common Center of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Unity in these Nations. They are truly tender of our Ministry, rejoice in our Labours, and in the Gifts and Graces of able and faithful Conformists, rebuke Backbiters and Vilifyers of our Ministry; and as they have opportunity, some of them hear and join with us and our Churches.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the time of the late King <hi>James</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> did confess its Error in being severe to the Nonconformists. This is plain from a certain Pamphlet published in the late King's Reign, entituled, <hi>A Letter to a Dissenter, upon occasion of his Majesty's late graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Declaration of Indulgence.</hi> The Words there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>page</hi> 8. are these following; <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>convinced of its Error in being severe to you; the Parliament, whenever it meeteth, will sure be gentle to you: the next Heir bred in the Countrey which you have so often quoted for a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Indulgence: A general Agreement of all thinking Men, that we must no more cut our selves off from the Protestants abroad, but rather enlarge the Foundations upon which we are to build our Defences against the common Enemy; so that in truth all things seem to conspire to give you Ease and Satisfaction,</hi> &amp;c. This is to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the general Sense of the Conforming Nobility, Gentry, Commonalty, and Clergy, in the time of the late King's Reign: for so really it was, as is well known. Now here
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:93774:61"/> the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth confess its Error towards the Dissenters, and to have erred not in some slight and trivial Matters, but in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters touching the Foundation; and sees a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of enlarging its Foundations, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently of taking in the Nonconformists, and making them constituent Parts of the Church with her self. Either then the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists are upon one and the same Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation with our selves, or they deserve to be; and it is through no fault of theirs that they are not: Being upon the same Foundation, we cannot be against their Ministry and Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but we must needs be against our own, and overthrow the Common Protestant Cause, Religion, and Interest in this Nation, and consequently in all other Nations and Countries, what in us lies; and in being for their Ministry, we are for our own.</p>
            <p n="4">4. These Scriptures set together, prove it a Duty, <hi>viz. Hear, and your soul shall live,</hi> Isa. 55.3. <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midst of them,</hi> Mat. 18.20. <hi>I charge thee before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, preach the word, be instant in season, out of season,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.1, 2. <hi>Though I be free from all men, yet have I made my self servant unto all, that I might gain the more: And unto the Jews I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are under the law, as under the law, that I might gain them that are under the law; to them that are without law, as without law, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not without law to God, but under the law to Christ) that I might gain them that are without
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:93774:62"/> law: To the weak became I as weak, that I might gain the weak. I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means save some: And this I do for the gospel's sake,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Communion of Saints</hi> is a principal Part of the Catechism, and of the common Creed of <hi>Christendom;</hi> it is a Fundamental in true Religion, most frequently repeated in all Conforming Congregations. Now we do not duly believe and practise this Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, unless we hear and join with the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming Brethren in the Word, and Prayer, d Sacraments, as we have Call and Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, they being visible Saints, and there being nothing in their way of Worship, but what is either laudable or tolerable: God doth own and approve their Ministry and Meetings, and is graciously present with them.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Objections Answered.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. The Dissenters refuse Subjection to the Governors of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore it cannot be safe for us to hear and join with them. <hi>Answ.</hi> This is plainly not true; for under God His present Majesty is sole Supreme Governor of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ruling all Estates according to Laws enacted by common Consent in Parliament; witness the old Oath of Supremacy, and the 37th Article of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in these words, <hi>The King's Majesty hath the chief Power in this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and other his
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:93774:62"/> Dominions. Unto whom, the chief Government of all Estates of this Realm, whether they be Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical or Civil, in all Causes doth appertain, and is not, nor ought to be subject to any Foreign Jurisdiction.</hi> The Dissenting Ministers gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally subscribe this Article; and it is notorious that they are duly subject to His present Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, pray heartily for him, pay Taxes, bear all legal Charges, and are more upright and cordial to the present Government, than many of the Conformists are. If you deny His present Majesty to be chief Governor of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> you then bring in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and unhinge the Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Though the King be Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor by the Sword, yet Bishops are Supreme Governors of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by the Word. <hi>Answ.</hi> Bishops have no Authority but what is ministerial and subordinate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot be Supreme Governors: They are under Law to God, and they are under Law to the King as God's Vicegerent. If you suppose them Supreme Governors of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> you suppose them Popes, that is, Antichristian Prelates, exalting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves above God, and above the King his Vicegerent. <hi>Abiathar</hi> the High-Priest was not Superior to, nor Co-ordinate with King <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> but his Subject, and therefore for his Crime was justly deposed by him, and <hi>Zadock</hi> put in his room.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:93774:63"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. The Dissenting Ministers have not just and valid Ordination, as being Ordained by meer Presbyters without a Bishop. <hi>Answ.</hi> God hath no where declared that there cannot be just and valid Ordination without a Bishop, and therefore the contrary Doctrine must needs be Erroneous. Accordingly all true Protestants own and approve Ordination by Presbyters without a Bishop, (as is used in the <hi>Dutch, Helvetian, French,</hi> and <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Churches) to be just and valid, and not defective in any thing absolutely necessary. The Church of <hi>England</hi> doth not allow the Ordination of Presbyters by a Bishop only, without the presence and concurrence of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assistant Presbyters, who do equally Impose Hands with the Bishop: And the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do not allow Ordination by all Presbyters promiscuously, but only by Senior Presbyters, such as for their Age, Experience, Gravity, Wisdom, Ministerial Ability and Fidelity, and exemplary Vertues, are Heads and Chief Men among them, and a kind of Fathers to the Younger Sort, The principal thing in a Minister of Christ, is not External Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but Ministerial Ability and Fidelity; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Ordination is not principal but subser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient: And where is Ministerial Ability and Fidelity, with the consent and liking of the People, and the protection and countenance or permission of the Magistrate, with Imposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hands, and Fasting and Prayer by Senior Ministers of known Wisdom, Gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:93774:63"/> Piety, and exemplary Vertue and Ability; either this is just and valid Ordination, or there is no such thing as Ordination, neither can it be declared what it is. Now this is the Ordination in use among the Dissenters. And indeed able and faithful Presbyters are, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture-phrase, Bishops; <hi>Acts</hi> 20.17, 28. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. We who are Conforming Ministers cannot hear and join with the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists without breach of our Oath of Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Obedience to the Ordinary. <hi>Answ.</hi> That Oath binds us but to obey the Ordinary in things lawful and honest: And to hear and join with the Nonconformists as we have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, is neither against Law nor Honesty, but rather laudable, pleasing to God, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Soul, and the true way of Peace. The Ordinary is not Supreme, but an Officer appointed by the King and State touching Church-matters, he is under Law to God, and to the King and State: If he enjoin or forbid us any thing contrary to Law, we owe him no Obedience. Our Oath to him binds us to no new Duty, but only binds us more strictly to do what we had been bound by the Law to do, in case we had not taken that Oath. The same Supreme Authority which makes the Ordinary, and gives him limited Power over us, doth declare in the Preamble of the late Act for Toleration, that the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty now enjoyed by the Nonconformists, <hi>may be an effectual means to unite His Majesty's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:93774:64"/> Subjects in Interest and Affection.</hi> Now our hearing and joining with the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists, is a countenancing of them, and of their present Liberty, and consequently it tendeth to the Union of Protestants in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest and Affection, in the Judgment of the King, and of both Houses of Parliament, and consequently of the Ordinary himself; for by the Ordinary is meant the Bishop of the Diocess, who is one of the House of Lords, and so hath a hand in making the Law. How can we disobey the Bishop by hearing and joining with those Men, unto whom the Bishop himself, as a Member of the House of Lords, doth by his consent to the Act of Parliament, give free Liberty, as an effectual means of uniting Protestants in Interest and Affection, and exempteth them from all Penalties, and from being prosecuted in any Ecclesiastical Court, for or by reason of Nonconforming to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. The Nonconformists are against all Church-Government by Bishops; and there can be no Church without a Bishop. <hi>Answ.</hi> The Nonconformists are not against all Church-Government by Bishops, for they have long desired that famous Archbishop <hi>Usher</hi>'s Model of Church-Government by Bishops and Presbyters might be established among us. But hitherto they could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, for there are a Party of Men in the Nation, some Clergy and some Laity, by
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:93774:64"/> Profession Protestants, whom the Piety and Moderation of such Bishops as Bishop <hi>Usher</hi> and Bishop <hi>Hall,</hi> doth greatly offend, and can by no means please. A limited Episcopacy the Nonconformists generally are not against; try and see if they will not accept and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly Conform to Archbishop <hi>Usher</hi>'s Model. That there may be a Church without a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, is plain from the <hi>Dutch, Helvetian,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant <hi>French</hi> Churches, and those in <hi>New-England.</hi> There is also the universal Church on Earth, and yet no one universal Pastor and Bishop on Earth. The Pope indeed claims to be so, but for that he is by Protestants justly charged with Antichristian Pride and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. There is also the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as comprising all the Christian People in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> but no one Man is universal Bishop to all the Christian People in <hi>England,</hi> nor are all the Bishops put together Governors of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but they are subject to the King, and Governed by Laws made by the King and Parliament, as hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared; and therefore it is not true that there can be no Church without a Bishop. The Church consisteth by Christian Faith, Hope, and Love, not as exclusive of Pastors and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, but as supposing and including them as God's Instruments for begetting and finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing these heavenly Graces: And nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders but that able and faithful Presbyters may be instrumental in God's Hands for begetting and finishing these heavenly Graces in thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of Souls, yea and much better than
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:93774:65"/> some Bishops, such as either cannot, or will not Labour in the Word and Doctrine; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Bishops, who are Idolaters, and such other as seek themselves and not the things of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 6. The Nonconformists have no Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in their way of Worship. <hi>Answ.</hi> Yes, but they have two Ceremonies of God's own Ordaining, Baptism and the Institution of Bread and Wine; and if God had not thought these two enough, he could easily have Ordained more; but he thought good to Ordain no more, and it must needs be a wise and safe way to keep to God's Ordinance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 7. The Nonconformists have no pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Liturgy, that is, no stinted Form of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayer and Administration of Sacraments. <hi>Answ.</hi> You will give the Minister leave to chuse his Text, and compose and methodise his Sermon; Why can you not also leave him to perform the other part of Ministerial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, respecting Prayer, Thanksgiving, and the Sacraments, by a stinted Form or not, as he himself is best able and thinks most meet? If his Words be grave, sound, scriptural, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, suited to common Edification, though not to each ones Fancy, your Duty is to mind your Heart, to purify that from Pride and carnal Prejudice, and evil Thoughts, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately to concur and join in all the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and be thankful. It is very desirable that all Ministers were of such Abilities, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:93774:65"/> at all times so prompt and full, as to need no stinted Form in publick; let those who are so able, not be abridged of their Liberty beyond their own Choice and Christian Prudence. The Nonconformists keep to Christ's own Words in the Act of Baptism, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the Words of Christ touching the Lord's Supper, and they keep to a stinted Form in Singing Psalms, and they read God's own Word in their Assemblies; and if they be able to Preach, they are able to Pray, and to suit their Prayer to the Edification of that People over whom they are set, and to whom they Minister. And therefore this can be no just Exception; they think they have much more reason to except against our way, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much in stinted Forms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 8. We who are Conformists, cannot hear and join with the Nonconformists with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out condemning our own way. <hi>Answ.</hi> It doth not follow, that because our Way is good, therefore their Way is not good; for as to external Modes, and Forms, and Things circumstantial, Sister-Churches, and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-Congregations may differ, and yet both be good and lawful. Twenty Ministers at the same time in distant Congregations may hit upon the same Text, and deliver the same substantial Doctrine, and yet their Words and Method and Composure may wonderfully vary, and all may be good and useful, and God more glorified by such Variety, than otherwise. Most conforming Congregations
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:93774:66"/> have no Organs; some have; must therefore one of the two necessarily be bad and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? The Churches in <hi>Holland,</hi> the Churches in <hi>Helvetia</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> the Churches in <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and in <hi>New-England,</hi> the Protestant <hi>French</hi> Churches, have different Ways, and Modes, and Forms, as to external Worship. If one be good, must we therefore condemn all the rest as sinful? What is sinful and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God, we may in no wise conform to; but what is neither precisely commanded, nor precisely forbidden by God, may be done or not done, according as Christian Prudence shall dictate to be most convenient: In such Cases and Matters we are after the Example of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to be all things to all Men; and if we come to an Episcopal Church, do as they do; if we come to a Presbyterian Church, do as they do; according as <hi>Ambrose</hi> advised <hi>Augustine, Ad quancunque ecclesiam veneris, ejus morem serva, si, &amp;c.</hi> To what Church soever thou shalt come, observe its way and manner, if thou wouldst neither offend others, nor have others to offend thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 9. If the Nonconformists will preach in the Church, I will readily hear them; but to hear them in Barns and private Houses, and the like places, I will not, I am against it. <hi>Answ.</hi> We cannot follow a better Pattern than Christ: Now he preached not only in the Temple and Synagogue, but in private Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and sometimes upon a Mountain, and by the Sea-side out of a Ship, the People standing
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:93774:66"/> upon the Shore; and he never declined Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to more or fewer in any convenient place suitable to the Occasion. The places in which the Nonconformists preach, some of them are goodly Edifices, some of them are publick Chappels, the meanest of them are not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally indecent, they best suit with their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances; and God being graciously present with them, the places where they assemble must needs be <hi>the House of God, and the Gate of Heaven,</hi> Gen. 28.10, to 18. Get them free leave to exercise their Ministry in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and they will willingly quit their Barns and other places; but if you exclude them from the Churches, you necessitate them to preach in other places; and by valuing the Word for the sake of the Place, rather than the Place for the sake of the Word, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that indeed you do not truly value God's Word. As it was no Shame to Christ to be born in a Stable, nor to his Virgin-Mother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was not their Sin but their Calamity, but all the Shame was to those that thrust them into the Stable: so it is no Shame for God's Ministers and People to worship him in a Barn, when they have no fitter Place to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God in; but the Shame is to those that might allow them better Places to worship God in, and will not, but thrust them into a Barn, and then make that a Cloak for their not hearing and joining with them.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:93774:67"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 10. There is no need of the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists Preaching, it doth more hurt than good, it may better be spared, the Conformist Ministers are full enow for the People of this Land. <hi>Answ.</hi> I confess that if all Places throughout the Nation were supplied by able and faithful Conforming Ministers, as some are, there would not be such need of the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists Preaching as now there is; but it is manifest to all discerning and impartial Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, that though there is no want of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, yet there is great need of able, holy, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, painful and exemplary Ministers in all the Diocesses of <hi>England;</hi> and pious Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists and Nonconformists Ministers have need of each others Labours, and the more humble and faithful they are, the more sensible of it. Never to this day did the Church over-abound with able and faithful Preachers, nor will to the end of the World, while the Followers of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> remain in the World, and many are called, but few chosen. Good Bishop <hi>Hall</hi> would use to say, You may as well complain of too many Stars in the Firmament, as of too many good Preachers in a County.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 11. The late Act of Toleration doth only tolerate the Nonconformist Meetings, it doth not approve them. <hi>Answ.</hi> It is plain from the Preamble of the Act, that it permits them as <hi>an effectual means to unite their Majesties Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Subjects in Interest and Affection;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:93774:67"/> it must needs approve them. For nothing that is not good and laudable, and worthy to be approved, can be an effectual means of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Protestants in Interest and Affection; so that the Nonconformists have as true Right to their places by the Law of the Land, as the Conformists have to theirs, they are both alike under His Majesties Protection, and do alike stand or fall with Him and His Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; their Religion is one, they have the same common Enemy, and are like to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py or miserable, strong or weak, according as they unite in God and His present Majesty, or do not unite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 12. The Dissenting Meetings are not true visible Churches of Christ. <hi>Answ.</hi> The 19th Article of the Church of <hi>England</hi> declares <hi>the visible Church of Christ to be a Congregation of faithful Men, in which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly ministred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Christ's Ordinance, in all those things that of necessity are requisite to the same.</hi> Now the Dissenting Meetings are visibly such Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and therefore it is impossible that they should be heretical, schismatical, and lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any thing necessary to the being of true visible Churches of Christ. If we deny them to be true visible Churches of Christ, we shall not be able to prove the Conformist Churches true visible Churches of Christ; for my part I am not able, and I despair to see it solidly and scripturally proved by any other.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:93774:68"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 13. Conforming and Nonconforming Churches are contradictorily opposite, as Light and Darkness, Christ and <hi>Belial,</hi> Heaven and Hell, and therefore both cannot be true Churches. <hi>Answ.</hi> Such as conform to God's Word, and such as do not conform to God's Word in the Substance and Foundation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are contradictorily opposite, as Heaven and Hell, the Church of God and the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan; but they who equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to God s Law in the Substance and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Religion, and differ but about cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantial things enjoined by Man's Law, though really and for the main they be both Conformists, yet verbally and <hi>secundum quid</hi> they differ as Conformists and Nonconformists; therefore the grand difference is not between Conforming and Nonconforming Protestants, but between godly and ungodly Protestants, whether Conformists or Nonconformists. As for godly Men Conformists and Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists, they can bear with one another, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in each others Labours, and sincerely though not perfectly deny themselves, and mind and seek the things of Christ, and advance his Kingdom; but it is unregenerate, ungodly, Self-seeking, Saint-hating, sensual and worldly Men, whether Conformists or Nonconformists, that are the Plague of the Church, and Satan's chief Agents.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 14. It is fitter that the Nonconformists come over to us than we to them; we by yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:93774:68"/> to them shall harden them in their sinful Nonconformity, and shall displease our own Side, and not gain our Enemy. <hi>Answ.</hi> Be it supposed that Nonconformity is a Sin, will it therefore follow that we are not to do our Duty to God and them, and all that in us lies seek the Peace of the Church and the Publick Good? Rigid Conformists confess the Points scrupled by Nonconformists, to be in their own nature indifferent, neither commanded nor forbidden by God, and that the Church may <hi>well</hi> be without them: Moderate Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists confess the Church might <hi>better</hi> be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, if all both Rulers and People could be so content: but Nonconformists judge some of the things to be flatly sinful. Now on whom doth it lie to yield? They retaining their own Principles, cannot yield and come over to us; we retaining our own Principles, may come over to them, and join with them in the Word, and Prayer, and Sacraments, as we have Call and Opportunity; and in so doing, we gain them so far as it lies in us to gain them; we please God, which is Motive sufficient, and cannot but have a good end and effect. If they make an ill use of our Condescension, that is their Sin, for which they must answer to God, who will not fail to accept and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our good Deed: and if Conformists be displeased with us for doing our duty, shall we therefore desist from it? The question is not, whether they sin in not conforming? but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing to each other their different Thoughts and Opinions about Conformity, what is the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:93774:69"/> duty of both sides as to mutual Peace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord? They are so prudent as in the course of their Ministry to insist upon those Points in which both sides agree, as being sufficient for Edification; and therefore we may safely join with them in publick Church-duties as we have occasion, without receding from our own Principles, without breaking any Law divine or humane; and therefore it will lie at our door if we do not; we sin against one Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith, <hi>The Communion of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 15. The Nonconformists preaching is generally Mystical, Enthusiastical, and Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistical, therefore I care not to hear them. <hi>Answ.</hi> You mean (I suppose) they preach up the Doctrines of Original Sin, Regeneration, and Mystical Union with Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I wish we did preach more on such Subjects, which are so necessary in order to Salvation, and which come more home to the Conscience; whereas that which we call <hi>Rational</hi> and <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious,</hi> does only affect the Fancy; the truth is, too many of us preach up <hi>Seneca</hi> more than we do St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 16. Can you give an instance, an example of what you press and exhort to? <hi>Answ.</hi> Yes, a famous one recorded in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Confessions of three Parties of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants in <hi>Poland,</hi> some following the <hi>Augustan</hi> Confession, some following the <hi>Helvetian</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and some following the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Confession; and being sensible of the evil and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:93774:69"/> sad effects of their Divisions, the leading Men of each Party came to an Agreement as to Doctrine and Points of Faith, and permitted to one another diversity in Rites and external Modes, and so became one, and did preach, and pray, and communicate with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and did greatly flourish in the midst of Popish Adversaries and <hi>Arian</hi> Hereticks, and Enemies of all sorts. See for this <hi>Corpus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess. par.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 163. <hi>par.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 215. <hi>Paraei Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. cap.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 17. A downright and thorow Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formist I love, a downright Nonconformist I can fence my self against, and do not much fear nor care for: but a doubting Conformist, neither Fish nor Flesh, halting between God and <hi>Baal,</hi> and true to no side, I cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure; the Church is in most danger from such, from such good Lord deliver us. <hi>Answ.</hi> You do well to be against Double-mindedness and Hypocrisy, and halting between God and <hi>Baal;</hi> I pray stick to this Principle, and be for no Side, for no Sect and Party against im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Truth and Godliness, and permit me and others to serve you, and both Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists and Nonconformists in Love; and all that lies in us to live peaceably with all Men, and to be one with God, and all good Men against the World, the Flesh, and the Devil. Remember the Communion of Saints is an Article of Faith twice repeated in Conforming Churches each Lord's Day, and at other times.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:93774:70"/> Let us all agree to practise this one Article of Faith impartially, and it will heal all our Breaches and Divisions: I press no one to go against his own Principles and the Dictate of his Conscience, but only in times of great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, and of many Sects and Parties, and contrary Ways and Interests, to be an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Christian, and to abound in holy Love and Self-denial, and true Zeal for the Peace of God's Church in this Nation, and for the publick Good. Certainly St. <hi>Paul</hi> did well in circumcising <hi>Timothy, Acts</hi> 16.3. and yet else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he counts Circumcision <hi>a weak and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Element,</hi> Gal. 4.9. and tells the <hi>Galatians, If ye be circumcised. Christ shall profit you nothing, Gal.</hi> 5.2. Was therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> neither Fish nor Flesh, but a double-minded Hypocrite? Judge not according to Appearance, but according to Truth: have love to your Country, value Persons by their insides.</p>
               <p>Let us remember the Day of Judgment, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly converse with our Protestant Brethren, not be strange to them, serve them in Love; rejoice that Christ is preached, Souls saved and edified, and Satan confounded by the Ministry of Protestant Conformists and Nonconformists. Long for the good Day when all Sect-names shall be abolished, and till that can be, let us really and indeed be one in Love; embrace the Nonconformists as dear Brethren in Christ, make them freely welcome to preach in our Pulpits, encourage our People to hear them,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:93774:70"/> and hear and join with them our selves as we have Opportunity, and thank them for their Labours, and wish them all good Success, and extend our Charity to such of them as need, and in all things conform our selves to the Example of Christ. To him be Glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>